<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the ministers, teachers, and priests (so called and so stileing your selves) in Barbadoes by George Fox.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36426</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15690590</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15690590</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40299)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1593:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the ministers, teachers, and priests (so called and so stileing your selves) in Barbadoes by George Fox.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>69 [i.e. 79] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Contains numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Persecution.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO THE Miniſters, Teachers, AND PRIESTS, (So called, and ſo Stileing your Selves) IN BARBADOES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> GEORGE FOX.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1672.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:104399:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104399:2"/>
            <head>To the Miniſters, Teachers and Prieſts (ſo called, and ſo ſtiling your ſelves) in <hi>BARBADOES.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>COnſider ſeriouſly what a Charge you take in hand; do you not pretend to watch for and over Peoples Souls, and to preſent them to God? Have you preſented any to God? Nay, Can you preſent any to God? unleſs you be in the ſame Power and Spirit the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were in, which is an Immortal Power &amp; Spirit, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the <hi>immortal Soul to the immortal God:</hi> Do you pretend to watch for the ſpiritual and everlaſting Good of the People? but do not you watch more (whatever your pretences are) for their Goods (which you call your <hi>Revenues</hi>) then for that? O! how is it that there is ſo much raging (which wars againſt the Soul) amongſt you; yea, ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Fleſhly Luſts and Fleſhly Talk in the Hearts and Mouthes of People? Do you not pretend to cure their Souls, and to be the <hi>Curates</hi> of them? And if ſo, can you make the Soul Perfect? If you preſent them to God, muſt they not be perfect here? For, will you preſent an unperfect Offering to a perfect God? Do you not pretend that you Plough in Hope? And have you the Spiritual Plough, that turns up the Fallow Ground? And if ſo, how comes it to paſs, that there are ſo much Weeds upon your Ground? and that your Land lies fallow, in that there's ſo little Fruit brought forth to God? Look upon your Field every one of you; or whether are you idle, and do not plough, but beat the Air? and ſo do not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104399:3"/>you pretend that you threſh in Hope? Now have you the Spiritual Flayl? and if ſo, How chances it that there is ſo much Chaff? And do you not plead for Imperfection, and a Body of Sin and Death that people muſt neceſſarily have, while they live upon Earth? Then do you not plead for Chaff, and not for the Wheat? And look upon your Fields, and look upon your Vineyards, and ſee what abundance of Chaff there is: Have you not been the Seeds-men of the Fleſh, who ſow to the Fleſh; and not the Seeds-men of the Spirit, who ſow to the Spirit (<hi>For he that ſows to the Fleſh, muſt of the Fleſh reap Corruption</hi> (and ſo look what a goodly Crop you have) <hi>and he that ſows to the Spirit, he reaps Life Eternal.</hi> But do you believe, that every one hath a meaſure of the Spirit for you to ſow to? And do you believe, that every one is enlightened by Chriſt Jeſus, the Light, and their Saviour, that you may turn them from <hi>Darkneſs</hi> to the <hi>Light,</hi> and from the Power of the <hi>Devil</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> or rather, that you turn them from the Power of <hi>God</hi> to the <hi>Devil,</hi> and from the <hi>Light</hi> to <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> Examine your ſelves, and conſider; for you muſt give an Account to God.</p>
            <p>Have you heard Chriſt's Voice and God's Voice imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from Heaven? Hath he ſent you to Preach, or have you ran before you were ſent? And have you not ſpoken, and yet God never ſpoke to you? and ſay, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> as thoſe did who were reproved in <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.21. or, Have you been called of God as <hi>Aaron</hi> was; or, Have you taken that Honour upon your ſelves, having a Call of Men, and not as <hi>Aaron</hi> had? And Chriſt ſaith to his Apoſtles, <hi>Go and teach all Nations;</hi> and elſe-where he ſaith, <hi>The Goſpel muſt be preached amongſt all Nations,</hi> Mark 13.10. Now, did Chriſt ſet his Apoſtles down in Pariſhes, for ſo much a Year, that the People ſhould be like a Free-hold, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104399:3"/>that the People ſhould be Tenants for Life, or until they could hear of a bigger Benefice? Is this your Practice, or theirs, to wit, the Apoſtles of Chriſt? Now conſider, Chriſt (I ſay) ſaith, <hi>Go teach all Nations:</hi> Have you obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Commands, or have you heard his Voice (as was ſaid before) or are you of thoſe that have climed up ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way? and what doth Chriſt call ſuch?</p>
            <p>And if you be Miniſters of Chriſt, are you not Teachers of <hi>Blacks</hi> and <hi>Taunies</hi> (to wit, <hi>Indians</hi>) as well as of the <hi>Whites?</hi> For, is not the Goſpel to be preached to all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? And are not they Creatures? And did not Chriſt taſte Death for every man? And are not they Men? And was not he a Propitiation for the Sins of the whole World, as well as for the Saints? And ſo conſider, if the Goſpel was to be preached unto all (according as Chriſt commanded) why do you not teach the <hi>Blacks</hi> and <hi>Taunies</hi> here? You may (it may be) ſay, <hi>There is nothing to be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of them:</hi> What, have they not Souls for you to watch over and to cure? Are they not part of your Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners if not the greateſt part? And why do you find fault with the <hi>Quakers</hi> (ſo called) for teaching of their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and inſtructing them (to wit) the <hi>Blacks,</hi> and <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> and <hi>Whites?</hi> Does not the Lord ſay, <hi>That</hi> Abraham <hi>(he knew) would inſtruct his Family?</hi> And were not all his Men-Children to be Circumciſed? And are not all Men and Women now to be Circumciſed with the Spirit of God? But it ſeems your <hi>Blacks, &amp;c.</hi> are taught to Swear, and to Curſe, and to ſay, <hi>God Dam them;</hi> and many of them do Swear almoſt at every word, which they have been taught and learned here among you called <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (for they learn no ſuch kind of Speech in their own Country) And is not this ſad, that <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> ſhould have ſuch things amongſt them?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104399:4"/>For, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>You muſt not Swear at all,</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. and in <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. who taught them true <hi>Chriſtianity:</hi> And is it not the Duty of every Maſter of a Family, that ſo theſe may come to know their Duty to God, and to Man.</p>
            <p>Now firſt, Conſider your own Lives, and the End of your Preaching; whether you do not preach your ſelves, and for your ſelves, and ſeek theirs you preach to, and not them: Examine your Hearts truly before God; for to him you muſt give an Account: Have you not laid aſide this Command of Chriſt? namely, <hi>Freely you have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, freely give:</hi> and to invite the People, <hi>To come for Wine and Milk without Money and without Price,</hi> Iſa. 55.1. Now can you do ſo without Hypocriſie? How can you ſay ſo and not bluſh, when you will do nothing without Price, nor give any thing without Money, but will have ſo much a Year of every one in your Pariſh; or elſe, No Penny, No Pater Noſter. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>He coveted no mans Silver, nor Gold, nor Apparrel; but laboured with his Hands to ſupply his own Neceſſities, and the Neceſſities of others; and that he might be an Example to all that followed him</hi> (remember the words of our Lord Jeſus, how that <hi>it is a more Bleſſed Thing to Give, then to Receive</hi>) Acts 20.33, 34, 35. Now do you follow the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> herein? and is he your Example? What, do you think the People have no Eyes in their Heads to ſee you? And did not the Apoſtle ſpeak of a company, that were <hi>Heady, High-minded, and Lovers of Pleaſures more then Lovers of God, Self-willed and Covetous, that had got a Form of Godlineſs, but denyed the Power thereof, from whom he commandeth to turn away,</hi> read your ſelves in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>And truly Friends, I muſt needs ſay to you, I never heard ſo much debauch'd Language and Helliſh Lyes, as has been caſt unjuſtly and wickedly upon me ſince I came into this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104399:4"/>Iſland; which grieves my Soul, that ever ſuch ſhould be in Peoples Mouthes, and that you Miniſters ſhould glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be Entertainers (if not the Fomenters and Preachers) of them, where-with you have filled and poyſoned Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples minds, with wicked Lyes (I ſay) and falſe and filthy Slanders, and ſo corrupted them. O! how can ye be otherwiſe called, then Teachers of Lyes, and Lyars? even ſuch as love and make a Lye, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. and ſuch as are given up to believe Lyes; ſee their ſad End in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. And when you cannot with all your Lyes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke and ſtir up the Magiſtrate to Perſecution, then you perſecute us with your Tongues: But I hope, that many of the Magiſtrates will come to ſee you, ſo as that you ſhall not get to ride on them, and ſpur them on; for if you ſhould, you would make them your Drudges, juſt as the Prieſts of old ſpurred up <hi>Pilate,</hi> when they got over him to Perſecute and Crucifie our Lord and Saviour: But conſider it well, the ſame ſpirit and nature is in you that would Crucifie Chriſt, who is revealed now in his People: For have there not been <hi>Sauls</hi> among you, with their Packet of Letters, to Perſecute the People of God in this Iſland of late? read but Prieſt <hi>Leſsley</hi>'s, and ſome other Prieſts Petition, which they ſent or delivered to the Governour and Council here, a Copy whereof is hereunto annexed; And what hath he and others done this laſt Aſſembly convened, 'tis well known: Were not the Chief Prieſts the Authors of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Packet? for had he not a Packet from them? But now it ſeems you Chief Prieſts are grown more bold; for you can go your ſelves with your Packets to this laſt Aſſembly, I ſay. O! is it not a Shame, that you (who call your ſelves, <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi>) ſhould go to the Magiſtrate, to perſwade them to perſecute <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> And do you think, that the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104399:5"/>Magiſtrates have no other Work to do in this Iſland, even to do Juſtly, and to love Mercy, and walk Humbly with God; and to take Care of the Preſervation and Right Governing of the people in Righteouſneſs and in Holineſs; and that every man may be preſerved in their reſpective Eſtates; and to ſee that all do to others as they would have others do unto them; and to ſee that the Iſland may be preſerved in Peace; and to take Care of that which is for the Good of this Iſland, and Property of its Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants: As for Religion, that belongeth to God; for it came from God and Chriſt Jeſus (who is the Author of every mans Faith) and ſets up his Worſhip, which is in the Spirit and in the Truth, and is to rule in the Hearts of his People, who receive that Religion from above that is pure and undefiled in God's Sight; and ſo God and Chriſt muſt have a place in man to dwell in (to wit) the Heart, that ſo he may have his Due, his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Honour from and by them.</p>
            <p>But to return to your Sland<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, namely, <hi>that I ſhould hang ribbons upon peoples arms; and that I brought a young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from England to be nought with her, And that I ſhould lie with my Siſter,</hi> and ſuch-like ſtinking and filthy Lyes, have you and your Auditors reported of me, which no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber man (I am ſure) will give Credit to; being full well known, that I was never tainted or blamiſht with any ſuch Uncleanneſs. So that with <hi>David</hi> I may ſay, <hi>Falſe Witneſſes did riſe up, they laid to my Charge things that I knew not,</hi> Pſal. 35.11. Certainly, many of you are, and have been naught your ſelves this way, elſe you would have vertue in your mouthes, rather then have ſuch things, as a modeſt Ear abhors; yea, ſuch filthy ſtuff, and wicked Lyes as theſe (which came from the Devil, who is the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104399:5"/>Father of them) are your Pariſhes fill'd with. For I would have you know, that I abhor, deteſt, and ſcorn ſuch things; it being well known in <hi>England,</hi> I ſay, that I was never tainted with the leaſt Unclean action, nor thus taxed, till I came here amongſt you; but, what is in your own Hearts, that you caſt upon me, ſo that ye ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil Chriſts Words who foretold, <hi>They ſhould ſpeak all manner of Evil againſt you falſly for my Name's ſake.</hi> And indeed it is for Chriſt's ſake that you do it; So that we can be excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding glad, and rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, in that it is for his ſake, that we are thus evil ſpoken of. But know this, and be aſſured of it, the time will come that he will appear for our glory, and to your ſhame and confuſion. For We would have you to underſtand, that we have an eſteem of our Bodies, for our Bodies the Lord hath honoured with his mercies, and they are Veſſels of his honour, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt, and of God, and of the Holy Ghoſt, and not for Adultery and Fornication. Truly I could not but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſtand amazed, to hear of ſuch ſoul, beaſtly and unmannerly, and uncivil Language, as I have heard ſince I came here; What, is this Goſpel Teaching? O, but conſider, what the Scriptures ſpeak concerning ſlanderous Tongues, and of lying Lips, and of ſuch as have Venom under their Tongues, and the Poyſon of Aſps: What do you not believe that God will judge for theſe things, and ſweep away the Refuge of Lyes, and take the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach from off his People? Would you have the ſame Meaſure meaſured to you as you have done to me, and the reſt of us? Surely you have not had ſo much as Common Civility or Humanity, much leſs <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> for if you had had either, you would have come, and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to me, when I was in the Iſland, and not have railed againſt me behind my back, and incenſed others againſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104399:6"/>me: Was this Humane, or Chriſtianly, or Neighbourly done? Judge ye.</p>
            <p>But alas! what ſhall I ſay? I do very much fear, that the Hand of the Lord God will ſuddenly come upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you, with his ſwift Deſtruction: The Lord did vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit (and that not very long ſince) this Iſland with two ſore Judgments, the one, of <hi>Fire;</hi> the other, of the <hi>Plague:</hi> but alas! what Repentance? what Change have they wrought in you and upon you? What ſaith the Prophet of the Lord in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.9? <hi>When thy Judgments are on the Earth the Inhabitants of the World will learn Righteouſneſs.</hi> But alas! are you not rather worſe then you were before, and hardened more then you were before <hi>(Pharoah-like)</hi> as it is in the 10th verſe, <hi>Let Favour be ſhewn to the Wicked, yet will he not learn Righteouſneſs, &amp;c.</hi> O! it is not the work of Chriſt's Miniſters, to fall upon the Righteous, and perſecute the Innocent, and let Swearers, Drunkards, Whore-Maſters and Adulterers go free: And do you not pronounce the Bleſſing of God to be upon them, and Peace be unto them all, in the State and Condition where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they remain unconverted? For, are not the words ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral in the cloſe of your Service? And is this the beſt Entertainment you can afford Strangers, viz. <hi>To Slander and Belye them?</hi> Is this the beſt Proviſion you have for them in your Houſes? Surely theſe are very courſe Complements, from ſuch Perſons as are lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by others, and by themſelves too, as Men of no ſmall <hi>Breeding?</hi> But this is no <hi>good Breeding,</hi> nor manifeſts <hi>good Education;</hi> but beſpeaks the Educator not to be of Chriſt, nor of God; and this is the Production and Fruit of your Studdyings: Is this to follow the Apoſtle's Advice? who exhorts, <hi>To Studdy to be Quiet,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11. And 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15, 16. <hi>Studdy to ſhew thy ſelf approved of God, a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104399:6"/>Workman that needeth not be aſhamed, rightly dividing the Word of Truth: but ſhun Prophane and Vain Babblings; for they will encreaſe to more Ungodlineſs, &amp;c.</hi> And ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 12.22. <hi>Lying Lips are an Abomination to the Lord; but they that deal truly are his Delight.</hi> And in chap. 10.18. <hi>He that hideth Hatred with Lying Lips, and he that uttereth a Slander, is a Fool.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.5. <hi>Who ſo privily Slandereth his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, him will I cut off.</hi> Read <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28, 29, 30, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And conſider you, that call your ſelves Miniſters; Are the Scriptures of Truth of no value, of no uſe with you, nor with your People? which ſaith, <hi>That whoſoever is angry with his Brother without a Cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the Judgment: And whoſoever ſhall ſay unto his Brother,</hi> Racha, <hi>ſhall be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Council: But whoſoever ſaith unto his Brother,</hi> Thou Fool, <hi>ſhall be in danger of Hell Fire,</hi> Mat. 5.22. Now do you not know what this means? Ought not this to be more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly heeded by you Prieſts, and your Hearers, as you would not undergo the Penalty? or how can you? How dare you bring your Gift to the Altar, before you be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to your Brother? And you that perſecute, or go about to perſecute; are you not of the number of thoſe, <hi>that mingle their Sacrifices with Blood?</hi> O! what will become of you that perſecute and ſpeak all manner of Evil againſt God's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for <hi>Chriſt's ſake?</hi> Heſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are the Merciful; for they ſhall obtain Mercy.</hi> But what then will likely be your Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who ate Cruel and Unmerciful? Further, he ſaith, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the Meek; for they ſhall inherit the Earth.</hi> What then will become of you, who are Furious and Envious? Again, ſaith he, <hi>Bleſſed are the Peace-Makers; for they ſhall be called he Children of God.</hi> Then what will become of you, who ſtir up to Contention, Diſſention and Perſecution? this is no Goſpel, no Glad-tidings.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104399:7"/>
            <p>How can you ſay the Lord's Prayer, <hi>Forgive us our Treſpaſſes as we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us?</hi> So mark, you are no more forgiven then you do forgive, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>Depart you Curſed into Everlaſting Fire, &amp;c.</hi> Why, what's, the Matter? For, ſaith he, <hi>I was an Hungred, and ye gave me no Meat; I was Thirſty, and ye gave me no Drink, &amp;c.</hi> But you may anſwer and ſay, <hi>Lord, When ſaw we thee a Hungry, or a Thurſt, or a Stranger, &amp;c?</hi> Then will he ſay, <hi>Inſomuch as you did it not unto the leaſt of theſe, you did it not unto me: And theſe ſhall go into Everlaſting Puniſhment.</hi> There you ſee the Sentence is given already, you have heard it, and you may read it there, about the latter end. And Mark, If he dealt ſo with thoſe then, that did no good, how much more ſorer Puniſhment ſhall be inflicted on thoſe that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute ſuch, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſo you that do profeſs and make a Trade of Chriſt's words for Money, and perſecute him, where, and in whom he is made manifeſt; are not you made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in the ſight of the Son to be the very Antichriſt's, profeſſing Chriſt, and yet are found Enemies to him, and acting perverſly againſt him; and to be in the number of thoſe inwardly ravening Wolves in Sheep's Clothing, Chriſt ſpeaks of in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. and thoſe evil Trees and evil Ground, that bringeth forth nothing but Thiſtles, Bryars and Thornes, wherewith to rend, and tear, and prick the Lambs of God? And are you not of the number of thoſe, who build up, and adorn, and garniſh the Tombs of the Righteous, even Chriſt's Sepulchre, and obſerve his days, and their dayes, and yet perſecute him and the Saints?</p>
            <p>Where do you read, that Chriſt, or any of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, gave any Command unto you for to obſerve dayes unto them? And where was it ever the practice of any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104399:7"/>of the People of God all along the <hi>Bible,</hi> either to keep <hi>Chriſtmas-day,</hi> or <hi>Candlemas-day,</hi> or <hi>Childermas-day,</hi> or <hi>All Saints-day,</hi> or <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> or <hi>Lent, &amp;c?</hi> Had you not all theſe from the <hi>Popes?</hi> And how can you cry out againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> and yet live in the practice of thoſe things which you have from them, and that they have ſet up? If you will have a <hi>Maſs</hi> for your <hi>Candles,</hi> why not as well a <hi>Maſs</hi> for your <hi>Cows</hi> and your <hi>Horſes,</hi> your <hi>Sugar-Canes</hi> and your <hi>Potatos?</hi> We do not read that <hi>Iſaac</hi> obſerved his Father's day, or <hi>Jacob</hi> obſerved <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s day; or did the <hi>Jews</hi> obſerve <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s, or <hi>Moſes</hi>'s, or <hi>Aaron</hi>'s day; or that any of the Saints did obſerve the Apoſtles dayes, and called them, <hi>Holy-Dayes:</hi> Yea, did the Apoſtles obſerve Chriſt's day, or <hi>Stephen</hi>'s day, or <hi>James</hi>'s day, or any of the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt, and called them, <hi>Holy-dayes?</hi> Let us ſee the Scripture for it? For you pretend the Scriptures to be the Rule for your Practices; and yet, how dare you ſay ſo, and act quite contrary to the Scriptures of Truth? For did not the Apoſtle leave the People of God to their Liberty in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4, 5, 6, 7. concerning obſerving of days, <hi>He that obſerved a day, he was to obſerve it to the Lord; and he that did not regard the day to the Lord, they were not to judge one another about ſuch things:</hi> but you have thrown away this day alſo, that do act contrary, in judging and perſecuting one another upon this account,</p>
            <p>And doth not the Apoſtle judge and reprove the <hi>Galatians</hi> for obſerving dayes; and tells them, <hi>That they were Bewicht;</hi> and calls them, <hi>Fools?</hi> Gal. 3.1. <hi>O fooliſh</hi> Galatians! <hi>who hath bewitched you, that you ſhould not obey the Truth?</hi> And chap 4.10, 11. <hi>Ye obſerve Dayes, and Times, and Moneths, and Years; I am afraid of you leſt I have beſtowed upon you Labour in vain,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:104399:8"/>
            <p>How came you to be ſo wiſe, as to obſerve them, and compel others to obſerve them? do you not make your ſelves wiſer then <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or any of the <hi>Apoſtles?</hi> What Wiſdom is this think you, that you ſhould by it force People to obſerve dayes? came not this Power and Wiſdom firſt from the <hi>Pope,</hi> and not from the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> nor from <hi>Chriſt Jeſus?</hi> if you have it from <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> let us ſee where it is, convince us with Scripture? And where, I ſay, do you find in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> or his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did ordain the day you call <hi>Chriſt-Maſs,</hi> and the reſt of the dayes attending it, which you call, <hi>Holy-dayes?</hi> But, to ſay the Truth, you may rather term them <hi>Unholy,</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Ungodly,</hi> and <hi>Debaucht Heatheniſh Practice:</hi> So that, whereas you pretend to Honour the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> in and by them, you do no other indeed but diſhonour him, and do <hi>Perſecute</hi> others that will not do as you do, and ſo break the Command of God, who ſaith, <hi>Six dayes ſhalt thou labour, &amp;c.</hi> and here your Command is, that they muſt play more then Six Dayes. Now tell me, if you can, how many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of years after Chriſt and the Apoſtles were theſe days firſt obſerved as <hi>Holy-dayes,</hi> and ſet apart to be kept as you do now keep them.</p>
            <p>O! the Whoredoms, and Debauchery, and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Exceſs, Senſual Pleaſures, Carnal Delights, Carding, Diceing, Dancing, that theſe dayes are filled up with; ſo that the <hi>Devil</hi> hath more Work done him in theſe dayes then in many other dayes before or after. So, let the Witneſs of God in your Conſciences anſwer, Yea or Nay, and let all Sober People judge, whether or no I ſpeak not Truth, when I ſay, God is more diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and his Name prophanened, and taken in vain, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104399:8"/>blaſphemed more in the twelve Holy Dayes (ſo called) then in three times the number of them; let, I ſay, your Conſciences and all ſober people judge: So here you may ſee how the Apoſtle judged them that did <hi>obſerve</hi> days. But, conſider, whether or no doth the Kingdom of God ſtand in Meats, and Drinks, and Waſhings, and in Days; Nay, nay, it ſtands only in Righteouſneſs, and in Peace, and Joy in the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> which Kingdom all people are in the firſt place to ſeek after.</p>
            <p>And then concerning your Faſts in <hi>Lent, &amp;c.</hi> the Lord will ſay, <hi>Who required theſe things at your Hands?</hi> as it is in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.3, 4. <hi>Wherefore have we faſted, and thou ſeeſt</hi> (or regardeſt) <hi>not, &amp;c. Behold, ſaith the Lord, in the day of your Faſts you find Pleaſures, and exact all your Labours; ye faſt for Strife and Debate, and to ſmite with the Fiſt of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Ye ſhall not faſt as ye do this day, to make your Voices to be heard on high. Is it ſuch a Faſt as I have choſen? a Day for a man to Afflict his Soul: Is it to bow down his Head like a Bull-Ruſh? And wilt thou call this a Faſt</hi> (ſee the Contents of the Chapter above, where it is reproved for Hypocriſie) <hi>But is not this the Faſt that I have choſen, ſaith the Lord, To looſe the Bands of Wickedneſs, to undo the heavy Burdens, to let the Oppreſſed go free, and that they break every Yoak? Is it not to deal thy Bread to the Hungry, &amp;c.</hi> Now, whether your Faſt be ſuch, yea, or nay, let your own Conſciences judge.</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle commands us <hi>to pray every-where, lifting up holy hands, without Wrath, or Doubting,</hi> 1. Tim. 2.8. Now conſider this, are not your hands like thoſe fiſts of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs? and are you not full of Wrath and Doubting? or are your Hands Clean and Holy? Let the Witneſs in your Conſciences judge, and ſee if thoſe Actions and Practices be not found among you as was amongſt them,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104399:9"/>whom the Prophet ſpeaks of here, which is called Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, as was ſaid before.</p>
            <p>And, did not <hi>Judas</hi> carry the bag who was a Thief, who betray'd his Maſter? And, are not they for his Bag and Money, to hold it by intayle, even all, who are the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayers of Chriſt now in this day, where he is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in his People? I ſay, do they not betray him now, and ſeek to crucifie him in his members? or his members for his ſake? And is it not the Son of Perdition ſpoken of 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 23. <hi>who exalts himſelf above all that is called God? whom Chriſt will deſtroy with the breath of his mouth, and the brightneſs of his coming;</hi> Look into your ſelves, and read this if you can. But are not ſuch now worſe then <hi>Judas</hi> who carried the Bag? for we never read that <hi>Judas</hi> perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted any for not putting into his bag (as too too many now a dayes do) and have done, who will not go without the bag. And are not all ſuch Tranſgreſſors of Chriſt's Command, who bids them go without a bag or Scrip; and, Freely you have received, Freely give. How will ſuch anſwer Chriſt (think you) at the day of Judgment, when they are brought before his Throne, and before him at his Judgment Seat, who then will ſay unto them, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part you Curſed, &amp;c.</hi> but to his Sheep on his right hand, <hi>Come ye Bleſſed of my Father, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo enter thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Joy of the Lord, and the other into everlaſting Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, who have been perſecuting others for Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the living God in Spirit and in Truth, which Worſhip Chriſt Jeſus ſet up above 1600. years ſince, as you may read in <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24.</p>
            <p>Now Friends, to look into your Families and into your own Practices, are not we to ſee, that firſt you are to be approved before you do miniſter, both you and your Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies? For, are we not to try all things, and to follow you
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104399:9"/>no farther, then you follow Chriſt? And, were not <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> accounted Noble, in that they ſearcht the Scriptures, to ſee whether or no that which the Apoſtle had deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them, were according to the Law and the Prophets; And muſt we be more ignoble then they, think you? and now to try, whether you are in the ſteps of the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and of Chriſt and of the Apoſtles, or in the ſteps of thoſe Falſe Prophets they cryed out againſt; muſt we not try here by the Scripture? <hi>viz.</hi> by the Prophets words, and by Chriſt's and his Apoſtles Words.</p>
            <p>Then for the Trying you, the Apoſtle ſaith in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c. A Biſhop muſt be Blameleſs, the Husband of One Wife, Vigilant, Sober, of Good behaviour, given to Hoſpitality, apt to teach, not given to Wine, no Striker, not Greedy of filthy Lucre, but Patient, not a Brawler, nor Covetous, one that ruleth well his own Houſe, having his Children in ſubjection with all Cravity.</hi> Now, are you Blameleſs? are you Sober? of Good behaviour? and are you given to Hoſpitality? are you apt to teach? 'Tis Storied of one Parſon <hi>Gray</hi> of this Iſland [being at a Feaſt] the cuſtom was, for the Cups to be often handed about; one of Brandy, the other of Sack; but as for the Sack, the Parſon cared not much for it, having had enough of that Liquor: whereupon ſaid the pretended Reverend Parſon, when he ſaw the Cup of Sack come about again, which he cared not for, <hi>Lord;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>If thou wilt, let this Cup paſs from me;</hi> But ſhortly after, when a Cup of Brandy was coming towards him, ſaid he, <hi>Lord, if thou wilt, let as many as thou pleaſeſt of thoſe little ones come unto me.</hi> And after a while the Cup came about again, and firſt the Sack coming towards him (it being his turn to drink) ſaid he, <hi>Be not drunk with Wine wherein is Exceſes</hi> and ſo put it by; in regard he cared not for it; but the Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy coming next, ſaith he, <hi>but be filled with the Spirit,</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104399:10"/>drunk up the <hi>Brandy.</hi> O! abominable, that ever Men ſhould be given up to ſuch vile Affections, and to ſuch Atheiſtical Practices. But to return,</p>
            <p>Are you no Strikers, no Perſecutors? What, did not Brieſt <hi>Leſsley</hi> beat and ſtrike <hi>George Foſter</hi> very ſorely? the Truth of which is made evident to me under the hand of the ſaid <hi>G. Foſter</hi> before his Death, the Copy whereof is inferted in the End of this Book. Alſo one <hi>John Hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> Prieſt in this Iſland of <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> ſtruck one <hi>Charles Bream</hi> on the Head, as they rod together on the high-Way, by which ſtroke the ſaid <hi>Charles</hi> received much harm and prejudice, and not long after dyed. And that you are Perſecutors of God's Heritage, is evidently manifeſt, by the Humble Petition of <hi>William Leſsley, John Barnard, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Johnſon, John Hopwood, Mathew Cray</hi> and <hi>John Page</hi> to the Governor and Council of this Iſland of <hi>Barbadoes;</hi> the Copy whereof is likewiſe afflixed to the latter End of this Book.</p>
            <p>But once more to return; Are you not Greedy of filthy Lucre? are you not <hi>Brawlers?</hi> are you not Covetous? Let the People of this Iſland, and your own Conſciences judge.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſaith in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. <hi>The Love of Money is the Root of all Evil.</hi> Now ſee, if all this Evil hath not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from your Root, which is the Love of Money. And therefore ſaith <hi>Paul Epheſ.</hi> 5.3. but — <hi>Covetouſneſs let it not once be named amongſt you as becometh Saints.</hi> And yet, what is more named and practiſed among you, then Covetouſneſs, and covetous Practices; and this, I ſay, ſprings from your Root, which is the Root of all of you, as was ſaid before. And this is the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> that you Prieſts and others in Chriſtendom (ſo called) do endeavour to incenſe the Civil Magiſtrate againſt the Saints and People of God, to hold up the Root of all the Evil in you, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104399:10"/>is the <hi>Love of Money.</hi> Let the People and the Witneſs in your own Conſciences judge.</p>
            <p>Now next, as concerning your Families and Children; Are they ruled well? Do you rule your own Houſe well? are your Children in Subjection (mark) with all Gravity in that 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4. Is this ſo? Let the People and your own Conſciences judge. If that you cannot rule your own Houſes well, how are you like to take care of the Church of God? And are you not lifted up into Pride in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies? Let but the People and your own Conſciences judge. How can you but fall into the Condemnation of the Devil? And moreover, have you a good Report of them that are without, who are not of your Church? What good Report can thoſe that are without give of you? Are you Grave? are you not double-Tongued? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let your Conſciences and the People judge; For you muſt be approved, and then you may miniſter, being found <hi>Blameleſs</hi> of thoſe Evils.</p>
            <p>Now, concerning your Wives, are they Grave, not Slanderous? are they Sober? and do you rule your Own Houſe well? Let your own Conſciences and the People judge. Have you refuſed Prophane and Old Wives Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles? And do your Women adorn themſelves in <hi>modeſt Apparrel, with Shamefac'dneſs and Sobriety, and not with broid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Hair or Cold, or Pearls, or Coſtly Array; but (which becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth Women profeſſing Godlineſs) with Good Works,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 9.10. Are you not them, that ſuppoſe Gain to be Godlineſs? from ſuch the Apoſtle bids <hi>to turn away.</hi> 1 Tim. 6.5. Are you not of them that preach for the <hi>Love of Money?</hi> and would you preach without it? and is it not the <hi>Root of all Evil,</hi> which while ſome coveted after, they have err'd from the Faith, which gives Victory.</p>
            <p>And are you not of thoſe which preach no Victory
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104399:11"/>here over Sin? But was not the man of God to flee ſuch, and follow after Godlineſs and Righteouſneſs, <hi>Faith, Love, Patience, Meekneſs;</hi> Read <hi>Timothy</hi> for further Tryal and approving you and your Families, and alſo <hi>Titus</hi> 1.6, 7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are you <hi>Blameleſs,</hi> having Faithful Children, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of Rioting and Unrulineſs? Let your own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and the People judge, whether theſe things be ſo or no. You profeſs your ſelves Stewards of God, but are you Blameleſs? Are you not Self-will'd and ſoon angry? Let your Conſciences, and the People judge. Are you Lovers of Good Men? If ſo, why do you raiſe or broach Slanders of them, and Lyes of Good Men? Are you Juſt, Holy, Sober, Temperate? Let the People and your own Conſciences judge.</p>
            <p>Are you not thoſe that preach for Filthy Lucre ſake? And, where are your Epiſtles written in one anothers Hearts, that you are all void of thoſe foregoing Evils, mentioned before? But rather, are you not like them, that were always Lyars, Evil Beaſts, and Slow-Bellies, which were to be rebuk'd ſharply? Read the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Titus</hi> throughout, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.18. Doth not the Apoſtle command us to mark ſuch? and avoid ſuch as ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own Bellies; and by good Words and fair Speeches deceive the Hearts of the Simple. And were they not ſuch, as made Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among the People, and Offences? Would you preach but for your Bellies? For if you ſerve the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, you would keep his Commands, who ſaith; <hi>Freely you have received, freely give,</hi> Tit. 3.19. and Phil. 3.19. Read that, and conſider whether you are not ſuch as the Apoſtle and People of God have often wept about. For do not you mind Earthly things? and do not you
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104399:11"/>preach for Filthy Lucre? So, is not your Godd your Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies? and what is like to be your End? you may read there. For would you preach without theſe things? And if you be otherwayes minded, why do not you follow the Apoſtle's Example? For the Apoſtle, when he had ſpoken in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. concerning his Powers, he told them, <hi>that he uſed none of thoſe things;</hi> nor did he write that it ſhould be ſo done unto him; For he would rather dye, then any man ſhould make his glorying void, for he had kept the Goſpel of Chriſt without Charge, and would not abuſe his Power in the Goſpel. Now have you kept the Goſpel without Charge? Look over whole Chriſtendom, both among <hi>Papiſts and Proteſtants, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſts.</hi> And did not the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>He wrought with his hands, to ſupply his own Neceſſities and the Neceſſities of others?</hi> And in <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5.29, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You dare not ſay, but that he was a True Prophet, nor dare you ſay, he preach't and propheſied to People for <hi>Maintenance;</hi> or can you make good, he had any thing given him for Publiſhing his Book? <hi>Shall not I viſit for theſe things,</hi> ſaith the Lord; <hi>Shall not my Soul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this? A Wonderful and Horrible Thing is committed in the Land, the Prophets propheſie Falſly, and the Prieſts bear Rule by their means, and my People love to have it ſo: What will you do in the End thereof?</hi> Now conſider? Do you not bear Rule by your meanes? and do not the People love to have it ſo? and was not this a horrible thing committed in the Land, and reproved by the true Prophet? And yet will you hold up that which he reproved. And read <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. Such as propheſie Lyes in the Lord's Name, and the Lord never ſent them, and he never commanded them. And <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. He ſaith both the Prophet and the Prieſts were Prophane, and the Lord had found their Wickedneſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104399:12"/>in his Houſe; and therefore, thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will feed them with Wormwood, and make them to drink the Water of Gall: For, from the Prophets of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>is Prophaneneſs gone forth in all the Land: I never ſent them</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>yet they ran; I never ſpake to them, yet they propheſied: How long ſhall this be in the Hearts of the Prophets, that propheſie Lyes? Yea, they are Prophets of the Deceit of their own Hearts, which think to cauſe my People to forget my Name by their Dreams.</hi> And theſe were they that did ſteal the Word from their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? <hi>Behold, ſaith the Lord, I am againſt them; for theſe are them that cauſe my People to Err.</hi> Read the Chapter throughout, and read your ſelves by it; wherein, as in a Glaſs, you may ſee your Phyſiognomy, whether you be like <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> or them.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. He was a true Prophet, and ſpoke forth freely; And do not you make a Trade of his words? read from the 10th verſe to the end; his Watch-men are blind, they are all ignorant, they are all Dumb Dogs, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bark, ſleeping, lying down, loving to ſlumber; yea, they are greedy Dogs that never have enough, and they are Shepherds that cannot underſtand; they all look to their own Way, every one for his Gain from his Quarter [Mark that] who looks for his Gain from his Quarter. Are ye not found among them, walking in their Steps? <hi>Come,</hi> ſay they, <hi>we will fetch Wine, and we will fill our ſelves with ſtrong Drink, and to morrow ſhall be as to day, and much more abundant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. you may ſee what Morter-Makers they were, and what Builders, and how that God would break down their Wall that they had built; even ſuch as had propheſied a Viſion of their own brain, a lying Divination, and yet the Lord had not ſpoken to them, nor ſent them: and theſe went to polute God's People
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104399:12"/>for Handfuls of <hi>Barley,</hi> and for Pieces of <hi>Bread,</hi> as you may read in the Chapter throughout. And ſee if you be not found in the ſteps of ſuch as the Prophet reproves, and who with your Lyes have made the Hearts of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Sad, and ſtrengthened the Hands of the Wicked, that he ſhould not return from his Wicked Way. But God will deliver his People out of your hands, and ye ſhall know, that he is the Lord.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. when the Lord ſent <hi>Ezekiel</hi> his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, to cry <hi>Wo</hi> againſt the Falſe Prophets and Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, who fed themſelves, and cloathed themſelves with the Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when they ſhould have fed the Flock; But the Diſeaſed they did not ſtrengthen, the Sick they did not heal, the Broken they did not bind up, neither brought again that which was driven away; but with Force and Cruelty have they Ruled: but the Lord will gather his Sheep from their Mouthes, and is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of them, and hath gathered many, that they may not be a Prey unto you any more; and he hath ſet one Shepherd over them, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> So read this Chapter throughout.</p>
            <p>And read <hi>Mich.</hi> 3. where you may ſee, whether or no you be not in the ſteps of them whom he was ſent to cry out againſt; <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord concerning the Prophets that make my People to Err, that bite with their Teeth, and cry</hi> Peace, <hi>and they that put not into their Mouthes, they prepare War againſt them.</hi> And have we not found it ſo? Did you not ſay a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> to us, and preach Peace to us, while we put into your Mouthes? but when we could not put into your Mouthes, did you not prepare War againſt us? and did not the Lord ſay, That the Son ſhould go down upon you, and it ſhall be dark unto you; the Prieſts teach
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104399:13"/>for Hire, and the Prophets divine for Money; yet you lean upon the Lord, and ſay, <hi>Is not the Lord among us? none Evil can come upon us:</hi> And therefore ſhall <hi>Sion</hi> for your ſakes be ploughed up as a Field, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Heap, and the Mountains of the Houſe as the high places of the Forreſt. So now, mark what Barrenneſs and Heaps of people comes to; let your own Conſciences and the People judge.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Mal.</hi> Chap. 2. And now, O ye Prieſts, this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment is for you; <hi>If ye will not hear, if ye will not lay it to heart, to give Glory to my Name (ſaith the Lord of Hoſts) I will ſend a Curſe upon you, and will curſe your Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; yea, I have curſed them already, becauſe you do not lay it to heart. Behold, I will corrupt your ſeed, and ſpread Dung upon your Faces, the Dung of your Solemn Feaſts, and one ſhall take you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with it.</hi> So conſider your ſelves, whether you be not under this Curſe, or no, by your practice.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Mat</hi> 23. There you may ſee how Chriſt taught the Multitude, and his Diſciples both; but take notice how we ſhall know them that walk out of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; read the Chapter throughout: <hi>They</hi> (to wit, the Scribes and Phariſees) <hi>loved to have the uppermoſt Rooms at Feaſts, and the chief Seats in the Synagogues, and greetings in the Markets, and to be called of Men Maſters, and to go in Long Robes, and that which they do is to be ſeen of Men: But be not ye called of Men Maſters; for, one is your Maſter, even Chriſt, and all ye are Brethren; and he that is greateſt among you, ſhall be your Servant, &amp;c.</hi> Mark, this Command do not you ſcoff at? And he that will not give you the Cap and the Knee (the World's Manners lying in ſuch things) you call them, <hi>Ill-bred Clowns:</hi> but ſee how many Woes Chriſt pronounceth againſt ſuch as walk in their ſteps:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104399:13"/>And if you had been in the Prophets and Chriſt's dayes, you would poſſibly have called them Railers. And you may ſee in the latter end of <hi>Matthew,</hi> what a Rage the chief Prieſts and Elders were in againſt Chriſt; though they could tell by Scripture, when <hi>Herod</hi> had gathered them together, where Chriſt ſhould be born: For you may ſee in the 27th Chapter, When the Morning was come, all the Chief Prieſts and the Elders of the People took Counſel againſt Chriſt Jeſus, to put him to Death.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. there aſſembled together the Chief <hi>Prieſt</hi> and Elders of the People unto the Pallace of the High <hi>Prieſt</hi> named <hi>Caiphas,</hi> and conſulted how they might take Jeſus by Subtilty, and ſo kill him. And <hi>Judas Iſcariot,</hi> one of the twelve, went unto the Chief Prieſts, and covenanted to betray him unto them for thirty Pieces of Silver, and ſo he delivered Chriſt unto them; For he came with a great multitude, with Swords and Staves from the Chief <hi>Prieſts</hi> and Elders of the People, and ſo apprehended him, and brought him before the High Prieſt, and Scribes, and the Elders of the People; And the Chief Prieſt, and the Elders and the Council ſought Falſe Witneſſes againſt Jeſus, to put him to Death, and yet found none; At laſt there came two Falſe Witneſſes, and ſaid, <hi>This Fellow ſaid, He would deſtroy the Temple of God, and in three dayes build it up.</hi> And the High Prieſt roſe up, and ſaid to Jeſus, <hi>anſwereſt thou nothing? What is it theſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt thee?</hi> And Jeſus held his peace. What would you have ſaid? would you not have anſwered, He was guilty? And the High Prieſt adjur'd him by the Living God to tell him, whether he was the Son of God; And when Jeſus confeſt the truth, then the High Prieſt rent his Cloaths, and ſaid, <hi>He hath ſpoken Blaſphemy, what think you?</hi> And they anſwerd, <hi>He was guilty of Death; And they ſpit
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104399:14"/>in his Face, and buffetted him,</hi> (Here is the Work of the Prieſts) <hi>and ſmote him with their hands, and mockt him, and ſaid, Propheſie to us, thou Chriſt, who it is that ſmote thee?</hi> And the chief Prieſts and Elders perſwaded the Multitude to ask <hi>Barabbas,</hi> and to deſtroy Jeſus the Juſt. And ſo, is it not the practice of you now, to let the Thieves, Murderers, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, and Drunkards at Liberty, and perſecute the Juſt? And after they had Crucified him, the <hi>chief Priests</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> came to <hi>Pilate</hi> flattering, and ſaying, <hi>Sir, We remember that this Dreamer ſaid, while he was yet alive,</hi> After Thee Dayes I will Ariſe again; <hi>therefore let the Sepulchre be made ſure, until the third day, leſt his Diſciples come by Night and ſteal him away, and ſo ſay unto the People,</hi> He is ariſen from the Dead: <hi>ſo the laſt Error will be worſe then the firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See what a pittiful Fright theſe Prieſts were in, whoſe Cauſe was not good. But when Chriſt was riſen indeed, and the Watch had acquainted the <hi>Chief Priests</hi> of all things that were done concerning Jeſus, then they aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled together with the Elders, and took counſel, and gave the <hi>Souldiers</hi> a large ſum of Money to ſay, <hi>His Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples came and ſtole Him away by Night, while they ſlept: So, if in caſe this ſhould come to the Covernours Ears, we will ſecure you,</hi> ſaid the <hi>chief Priests,</hi> and the reſt. See how they were Teachers of Lyes here.</p>
            <p>And after Chriſt was riſen, ſee what work the <hi>Priests</hi> made againſt his Diſciples in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> chap. 4. What an Aſſembly there was of them in examining the Apoſtles, and how they threatened them, <hi>That they ſhould ſpeak no more in the Name of Jeſus, nor teach:</hi> but their Anſwer was, <hi>Whether it was right to obey God or Man judge ye:</hi> So they threatned them, and let them go.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Acts</hi> 5. See how the High Prieſt was full of Indignation, and all that were with him, againſt the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104399:14"/>Apoſtles, and laid hands on them, and put them in Priſon. So this was the Work ſtill of the Prieſts all along you ſee, and how the Lord ſtill Delivered his People.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Acts</hi> 7. You may there ſee, the <hi>High Priest</hi> and his Council examined <hi>Stephen,</hi> and at laſt, put him to Death. So that you may ſee their Work was againſt <hi>Christ,</hi> and his, though they had a Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Acts</hi> 9. See there how <hi>Saul</hi> breathed out Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and Slaughter againſt the <hi>Diſciples of Christ;</hi> and how he went to the <hi>High Priest,</hi> and deſired Letters to go to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and he had his Packet with him; but the Lord met him by the way, and ſent him upon a contru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Arrand, as he hath met with many in theſe latter dayes; Praiſes be to the Lord forever. But afterwards, when <hi>Saul</hi> was turned <hi>Paul</hi> (which ſignifies, <hi>Marvelous</hi>) in <hi>Acts</hi> 14. you may ſee how the Profeſſing <hi>Jews</hi> ſtirred up the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and made their minds evil-affected againſt the Apoſtles; As its now the manner of Profeſſors this day (who are without the Poſſeſſion) to ſtir up the Rude Multitude againſt the Profeſſors and Poſſeſſors of <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>Acts</hi> 20. There you may ſee how the <hi>Jews</hi> laid wait for <hi>Paul,</hi> on purpoſe to deſtroy him: And in <hi>Acts</hi> 21. how the <hi>Jews</hi> cry'd out, <hi>Help Men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>against the Apoſtle; and the people ran together, and took</hi> Paul, <hi>and went about to kill him, had he not been ſecured by the Captain, who was a</hi> Heathen.</p>
            <p>And in Chap. 22. <hi>Paul</hi> there acknowledgeth what he was when he followed the <hi>High Priest;</hi> and how there were more then Forty Men that had bound themſelves with a Curſe, <hi>That they would neither Eat nor Drink till they had killed</hi> Paul; and this they declared to the <hi>Chief Priests</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> who did not reprove them; but the Captain delivered him again: For thoſe that had bound
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104399:15"/>themſelves with a Curſe were of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and of the Gang of the <hi>Chief Prieſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in Chap 24. See there how <hi>Ananias</hi> the High Prieſt and Elders came againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> with many Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but ſtill he was delivered out of their hands.</p>
            <p>And how the High Prieſt, and chief of the <hi>Jews,</hi> came to inform againſt <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Peſtus, Acts</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>And ſo you may ſee how they (to wit, the <hi>Priests</hi>) ſtill continued and perſiſted in their ſad Work of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and Blood all along, both againſt the Prophets of old, and againſt Chriſt and the Apoſtles then, and againſt Chriſt now, who is manifeſted in his Children and People.</p>
            <p>And here you may ſee that the Birth born of the Fleſh perſecutes him (all along, I ſay) that is born of the Spirit, from Generation to Generation.</p>
            <p>And what ſoul clamarous Words and corrupt Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage they had againſt <hi>Christ,</hi> and his <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles?</hi> which were the Fruit of the Evil Spirit, and ſo is now, where-ever it is; and with ſuch unfruitful Works of Darkneſs there is no Fellowſhip to be had, but rather to reprove them: And therefore, let all Bitterneſs, and Anger, and Wrath, and Clamour and Evil-ſpeaking be put away from you, with all malice, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.31, 32. and Fornication, and Uncleanneſs, and Covetouſneſs, let it not be once named amongſt ſuch as becometh Saints, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.3. and alſo, all Filthineſs, Fooliſh-talking and Jeſting, which are not convenient; but rather giving of Thanks to God through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the Redeemer. For this we know, That no Whoremonger, nor Unclean Perſon, nor Covetous Man (which is an Idolater) hath any Inheritance in the Kingdom of God and of Chriſt: and they that think, or ſpeak otherwiſe, are ſuch as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104399:15"/>deceive the People with vain words; and for ſuch things cometh the Wrath of God upon the Children of Diſobedience.</p>
            <p>Now, conſider all you that call your ſelves <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and others in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> ſo <hi>called; Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is the Seed's-Man, and he ſows the good Seed which is in Man's Heart: now ſome Hearts be a High-Way, and thoſe Fowls in them, that are bred by the foul ſpirit, take it away; and ſome is ſown upon Stony Ground, where's not much Earth, but is ſcorch't by the heat of Perſecution; and ſome again is ſown upon the Thorny Ground, Thorny Hearts, where it grows a while, and then the Thornes, the Cares of the World, choaks it; but that which is ſown upon Good Ground brings forth good Fruit abundantly, to the Glory of God and Chriſt, the Seed's-Man.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Christ,</hi> in a Parable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeaks of a Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, that ſowed good Seed in his Field, and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſaid, <hi>Didſt thou not ſow good Seed? whence then hath it Tares?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>An Enemy hath done this?</hi> They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, <hi>Wilt thou that we go and gather them up? Nay</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>lest ye gather the Wheat alſo, let both grow together till the Harvest.</hi> The Field is the World; the Good Seed are the Children of the Kingdom of Chriſt; the Tares are the Children of the Wicked One; the Enemy, that ſowed them, is the Devil; the Harveſt is the end of the World; and the Reapers are the Angels: So Chriſt, he would not ſuffer his Diſciples to gather the Tares, leſt, &amp;c. Now what's the matter with you and others, who will be Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers when Chriſt hath forbidden you, leſt you pluck up Wheat inſtead of Tares; ſeeing it is the Angels Work to ſever the Wheat from the Tares, and the Wicked from the Juſt? And therefore whoſe Servants have you been
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104399:16"/>in all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> who will venture the gathering of the Tares, and inſtead of them have been plucking up the Wheat; as witneſs all the Martyrs and Bloody Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſince Chriſt's time: but theſe Tares, at the End of the World, the Angels ſhall caſt into the Fire, where ſhall be Weeping, and Wailing, and Gnaſhing of Teeth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Luke</hi> 9.55. When <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſent to a Village of the <hi>Sameritans,</hi> to make ready for him, and they did not receive him, his Diſciples ſaid, <hi>Lord, Wilt thou that we command Fire to come down from Heaven, to conſume them, even as</hi> Elias <hi>did?</hi> but Chriſt rebuk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t them, ſaying, <hi>Ye know not what ſpirit ye are of; the Son of Man is not come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now mark, If the Diſciples of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> did not know themſelves what ſpirit they were of, who would have had Fire to come down from Heaven upon ſuch as would not receive <hi>Christ;</hi> how do you know what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit you are of, and all thoſe ſince the Apoſtles dayes, that do perſecute people about Religion, by Impriſoning them, &amp;c? Now had they and you known what ſpirit you are of, you would not <hi>Perſecute;</hi> but ſeeing you do not, therefore it is you will have the People of God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted; and ſo are under the Rebukes of <hi>Christ,</hi> who came to Save, and nor deſtroy: And therefore, ſince you do not know what ſpirit you are of your ſelves, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not truſt our Bodies, nor our Souls, nor Spirits in your hands: And you ſee you have no Command from Chriſt, or the Apoſtles, to <hi>perſecute;</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>All Power is given to me, both in Heaven, and Earth, &amp;c.</hi> What to do? <hi>To deſtroy the Devil and his Works, the Enemy, the Adverſary, and Deſtroyer of Mankind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt, he is ſo far from that, that he commands us,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104399:16"/>
               <hi>To love one another,</hi> and <hi>to love Enemies;</hi> but this Command hath been little regarded in <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt ſpake to ſuch as built the Sepulchres of the Prophets, and garniſht them whom their Fore-Fathers had killed; and yet theſe Builders killed the Son.</p>
            <p>Have not we the ſame Builders now, that would kill him, and perſecute him where he is revealed in his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Truly, ye bear witneſs, that you allow the Deeds of your Fore-fathers, who did kill them and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, built and garniſht their Sepulchres, that ſo all the Righteous Blood from <hi>Abel</hi> to <hi>Zacharias,</hi> yea, to this very day, will come upon this Generation of <hi>Perſecutors;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in our dayes we have ſeen ſad Examples, how the Lord hath cut ſeveral of them ſuddenly off, who have been found perſecuting his People and Beloved Ones, his dear Lambs.</p>
            <p>And ſaith Chriſt, <hi>The Servant that ſays in his Heart,</hi> My Lord delays his coming, <hi>and begins to ſmite his Fellow-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Eat, and be Drunken; the Lord will come in a day when he looks not for him, when he is not aware of it, and will cut him aſſunder, and will appoint him his Portion with Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> Mat. 12. And therefore take ye heed who ſmite the Servants of God, and Hand-Maids of God, leſt the Lord come in a Day, or in an Hour, when you are not aware, and cut you aſſunder with his ſharp two-edged Sword, and appoint you your Portion with Hypocrites and Unbelievers; and therefore the People of God are alwayes to be in a readineſs waiting for the Appearance of the Lord: Mat. 24. <hi>And Bleſſed is that Servant that the Lord finds ſo doing; he will make him Ruler over his Houſe, that gives them their Meat in due ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now conſider, you Strikers, this; and all you Smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Perſecuters, you do not watch for Chriſt's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104399:17"/>no, no: but you put the Day and Hour afar off, and you do not know how ſoon either of them may come; of cutting aſſunder, and of your Weeping, Wailing and Gnaſhing of Teeth, and your Portion, which you are like to have with Hypocrites.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Christ</hi> further ſaith, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. <hi>Thoſe mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which would not that I ſhould Raign over them, bring hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſlay them before me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now conſider this, you that will not have <hi>Christ</hi> to Rule and Raign in his People, no, nor in your ſelves; Do you think that you ſhall eſcape the Sword of his Judgments, and of his Mouth, and the Wrath of the Lamb? And did ever Chriſt, though he was called a Blaſphemer, and as <hi>Belzebub,</hi> and that he had a Devil, and a Deceiver; yet, though he had all Power in his Hands given to him, in Heaven and in Earth, yet he did not perſecute any of them, but rebuk't his Diſciples: Neither did he give any ſuch Command or Advice to his Apoſtles, but rather the contrary, <hi>viz. That they ſhould love one another, and love Enemies.</hi> Now then, who hath given you this <hi>Power,</hi> to perſecute and beat another mans Children and Servants? Let us know your Original and your Antiquity.</p>
            <p>Now, whereas you may ſay, <hi>That Lay-men, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick Men are not to meddle with the Scriptures; but you onely that have got the Original of</hi> Hebrew, Greek, and Latine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Anſwer,</hi> Was not the beginning of the Originals in <hi>Babel?</hi> For, was not all the Earth of one Language be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? And had not <hi>Pilate</hi> theſe Originals when he cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Chriſt? And did he not write a Title upon his Croſs in <hi>Hebrew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine?</hi> And had not he your
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104399:17"/>Originals? and was not he an Orthodox man, and yet could not ſee Chriſt? And did not the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> ſpeak <hi>Hebrew</hi> naturally? And the <hi>Grecians,</hi> was not <hi>Greek</hi> their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Language? and yet they could not ſee Chriſt, nor could any of the Prieſts open Scriptures to the People; but incenſed them againſt Chriſt, as you may ſee, <hi>John</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>And is it not ſaid in the <hi>Revelations, That the Beaſt and the Whore had Power over the Tongues?</hi> Rev. 13.7. And doth not the Apoſtle there call the Tongues <hi>Waters?</hi> Chap. 17.15. And in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. Doth he not ſay, <hi>That Tongues ſhall ceaſe?</hi> And where are your Originals then?</p>
            <p>Now the Original, viz. the Word, is not that it that makes Divines? for was not <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Divine</hi> a <hi>Fiſher-man?</hi> and who made him a <hi>Divine?</hi> was it not Chriſt the Word that made him ſo? For they had no Colledges, nor U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities, nor Schools, to ſerve <hi>Seven Years in,</hi> as <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick</hi> Men do; and when they are out of their Time, then they ſet up where they can have the beſt Trading.</p>
            <p>And was not <hi>Paul</hi> a <hi>Tent-Maker,</hi> and <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla Tent-Makers?</hi> and was not <hi>Luke a Phyſitian?</hi> and was not <hi>Mathew</hi> called from the Cuſtom? and <hi>Peter,</hi> and others of the Apoſtles, were they not <hi>Fiſher-men?</hi> and yet were they not Preachers? And were not <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Noah Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?</hi> and <hi>Iſaac a Husbandman</hi> and <hi>a Grazier?</hi> and was not <hi>Lot a Grazier</hi> and an <hi>Husbandman?</hi> and were not <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>David Shepherds,</hi> and did not <hi>Moſes</hi> keep his Father's Sheep in the Wilderneſs? and <hi>David</hi> his Father's? and was not <hi>Jacob</hi> a <hi>Shepherd</hi> twenty years with <hi>Laban</hi> his Uncle, whom he faithfully ſerved? and was not <hi>Eliſha</hi> a <hi>Plowman,</hi> and <hi>Amos a Herdſman,</hi> a Keeper of Cattel, and a Gatherer of Fruits? and what were the reſt of them?</p>
            <p>And ſo, were not theſe Lay-men, as you term them, and theſe Mechanick-men that gave forth the Scriptures?
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104399:18"/>And can you make a Trade of Lay-men's and Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick-men's words, whom you allow and approve of; and yet will not ſuffer Lay-men and Mechanick-men to Preach, and Teach, and Speak now adayes? I pray you conſider, and read the Scriptures, and read your ſelves: Did any of theſe ſerve Seven years at the School before they went to preach? and learn the Seven Liberal Arts or Sciences (whereof <hi>Muſick</hi> is one) are not they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted by you Univerſity men, as the Seven Seals of that Book ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelations?</hi> and ſo is the Arms of your Univerſity at <hi>Oxford;</hi> which is as much as to ſay, That you are the only Perſons that are fit to open thoſe Seals: and is not this to give <hi>John</hi> the Lye? who ſaid, <hi>None was found worthy to open the Seals of the Book, but the Lamb, the Lyon of the Tribe of</hi> Judah, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>But what Parſonages, or Vicaridges and Benefices had theſe Lay-men, theſe Mechanicks, theſe Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, theſe Graziers, Shepherds, Cuſtomers, Plowmen, Herdſmen, and other Tradſmen, for Preaching and giving forth theſe Scriptures? or, what had <hi>Paul,</hi> and his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Teat-Makers? or <hi>Peter,</hi> and his Fellow-Fiſher-Men? I pray you let's ſee ſome Scripture for your Revenues and Parſonages: Chriſt ſaith, <hi>They ſhall take no Scrip nor Purſe, no Money with them; and they ſhould be contented to eat ſuch things as are ſet before them.</hi> And is there any thing more in the whole World got by any Trade now adayes, by all them that ſerve Seven years, or by the Husbandmen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, now in the World, that get more by their Callings, than you do, who call your ſelves (and are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) <hi>Prieſts and Miniſters</hi> all Chriſtendom over, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> than you do (I ſay) by theſe Shepherds words, and Plowmen, Fiſhermen and Tent-makers words; (who never ſerved ſeven years
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104399:18"/>at your Colledges) which were given freely forth at firſt, by which you now get ſuch great Revenues, that you will not ſuffer any others, neither Shepherds, Plowmen, nor Husbandmen, nor Fiſhermen, nor Tole-Gatherers, hardly to meddle with their Fellow-Fiſhermen, Fellow Plowmen, Fellow-Husbandmen, Fellow-Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds words. I pray take the right Meaſure, and the right Weights, and meaſure your ſelves, and ſee whether you would be ſo ſerved your ſelves.</p>
            <p>And do you think that you can open ſuch men's words before mention'd with your Tongues and Languages now? Whereas <hi>Pilate,</hi> and the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Grecians</hi> could not open them then: and are there better Tools think you to open them now, then there were then? not a whit. It was ſaid by one of your acknowledg'd and own'd Fathers, St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> ſo called, upon that verſe, <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven ſuffers Violence, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith he to this purpoſe, <q>A company of poor Mechanick and Tradeſmen, Tinkers, Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Cobblers, &amp;c. do take the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by Violence, when ſuch great Doctors and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as we are thrown down to Hell.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But further, Is it not written in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.13, &amp;c. <hi>All thy Children ſhall be taught of the Lord, and great ſhall be the Peace of thy Children; In Righteouſneſs ſhalt thou be Eſtabliſhed, &amp;c. And many ſhall gather together amongſt them, but not by me, ſaith the Lord. Whoſoever ſhall ſo gather together againſt thee, ſhall fall for thy ſake; and no Weapon that is formed againſt thee ſhall proſper; and every Tongue that ſhall riſe up againſt thee in Judgment, thou ſhalt condemn, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now mark; Is not this fulfill'd now adayes upon them that are Taught of God? yea, by you Miniſters, ſo called.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:104399:19"/>
            <p>And in <hi>John</hi> 6.45. where Chriſt ſpeaking to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>It is written in the Prophets, They ſhall be all taught of God; every man therefore that hath heard and learnt of the Father cometh unto me.</hi> Now this we witneſs this day, and therefore it is that there is ſo much murmuring againſt us.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>The Word of God is nigh thee, even in thy Mouth and in thy Heart. That is the Word which we Preach,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>which every one is to Hear, and to Obey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle relates in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. when the profeſſing <hi>Jews</hi> mockt the Apoſtle, ſaying, <hi>They were drunk with New Wine; Peter</hi> anſwering, told them, <hi>it was the third Hour of the Day, and ſo not likely to be in Drink. But this is that which was ſpoken of by the Prophet</hi> Joel, <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the laſt dayes (ſaith the Lord) I will pour out of my Spirit upon all Fleſh, and your Sons and your Daughters ſhall Propheſie, and your young Men ſhall ſee Viſions, and your old Men ſhall dream Dreams; and on my Servants, and on my Hand-maids I will pour out in thoſe days of my Spirit, and they ſhall Propheſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this ſame we witneſs in our days, as the Apoſtles did in their days. And we ſee your Sun is turned into Darkneſs, and your Moon into Blood, verſe 20. and your Sun is gone down, and your Stars are fallen from Heaven, as was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied in the <hi>Revelations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>God at ſundry times, and in divers manners ſpake in times paſt unto the Fathers, by his Prophets, but hath in theſe laſt dayes ſpoken to us by his Son, who is Heir of all things, by whom the World was made, &amp;c.</hi> For as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22. that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord God raiſe up unto you of your Brethren, like unto me, him ſhall ye hear in all things whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo now, we do witneſs that God hath raiſed him up, and him we do hear; and ſo (I ſay) we do witneſs
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104399:19"/>the Teachings of God by his Son Jeſus Chriſt the Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lord: So that we are not now without a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and a Prieſt, nor without a Shepherd and a Biſhop, nor a Miniſter. And we do certainly know, That the Son of God is come, and he hath given us an Underſtanding, that we know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt; and this is the True God, and Eternal Life, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. and he hath given us an Underſtanding: ſo that we now find that Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Satisfaction in him, which we could never pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, neither for Gold, nor Silver, nor for Pearls; the beginning whereof is the Fear of God, and departing from Evil, as you may ſee in <hi>John</hi> 28. at large. And therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25. <hi>See that you refuſe not him that ſpeaketh; for if they eſcaped not who refuſed him that ſpake on Earth, much more ſhall not we eſcape, if we turn away from him that ſpeaketh from Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.7. <hi>To day if you will hear his Voice, harden not your Hearts, as in the Provocation in the Day of Temptation in the Wilderneſs, &amp;c.</hi> So we are to hear his Voice that ſpeaks from Heaven, yea, and that while it is to day, and not to put it off till to morrow. Now you that do ſo, and ſay, that there is no hearing of God's Voice, nor of Chriſt's Voice now adayes, and that there's no ſpeaking from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now adayes; are not your Hearts hardened? and have you not hardened them to the purpoſe? do not the Fruits of your Hearts beſpeak it with a loud Voice? And if God's and Chriſt's Voice be not to be heard now adayes, I would willingly know of you, how he doth exerciſe his Offices in his Church, namely, his Kingly Office, as he is ſole Head of his Church; and his Prophetical and Prieſtly Offices; and his Office of a Biſhop and Shepherd, who feeds them with Life, and over-ſees and rules them
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104399:20"/>by his Power and Spirit. Now do not ſay, He doth not exerciſe his Offices in his true Church, becauſe you do not feel the exerciſe of them in yours, who lies knocking at the Door of your hearts, as a Prieſt, and a Prophet, &amp;c. and you will not let him in; if ſo, how then can he exerciſe his Offices? and how can you hear his <hi>Voice</hi> when you harden your Hearts, and like the deaf Adder ſtop your Ears, and will not hearken to the Voice of the Charmer, charm he never ſo wiſely? And how can you ſee him, when you cloſe your Eyes, Phariſee-like, ſo that you are not like to ſee him exerciſe his Offices? but the Blind lead the Blind into the Ditch, which is a corrupting place; and there they corrupt, and plead for their Corruptions for term of Life. Whereas we can, and do now hear his Voice, and obey it; and ſo can love our Enemies in Obedience to Chriſt's Command, and love one another. And we know the Lyars, who ſay, they Love God, and yet Hate their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>He is a Lyar,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>For, he that loveth not his Brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen?</hi> 1 John 4.20. <hi>And he that hates his Brother is a Man-Slayer: And we know that no Man-Slayer hath Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life abiding in him.</hi> For as the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We know the Meſſage which we have heard from the Beginning, That We love one another; not as</hi> Cain, <hi>who was of that Wicked One, and ſlew his Brother: And wherefore ſlew he him? Becauſe his own Works were Evil, and his Brother's Righteous. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel not, my Brethren, if the World hate you,</hi> 1 John 3.11, 12, 13.</p>
            <p>And ſo, 'tis no Wonderment to us, that the World hate us; for ſaith Chriſt (the Heavenly Man) <hi>It hated Me firſt.</hi> And this <hi>Cain</hi> was the firſt Perſecutor about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and where-ever this Perſecuting is, we know, that is of <hi>Cain,</hi> of his Spirit, of his Nature, Seed and Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104399:20"/>from whence is the Reprobation, ſince the World began in the Devil and old <hi>Adam,</hi> out of Chriſt, ſince, I ſay, the World began; whereas the Election is in Chriſt, the Seed of the Woman, by whom the World was made, who was glorified with the Father before the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. But the Reprobation (I ſay) is in the Devil, and old <hi>Adam,</hi> that ſeed where all the Veſſels of Diſhonour are: Whereas they are the Veſſels of Mercy and of Honour, that have received Chriſt, in whom is the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction only.</p>
            <p>And therefore, as we ſaid before, Marvel not if the World hate us; as the Reprobate Seed hated the Elect Seed, <hi>Cain</hi> hated <hi>Abel,</hi> and <hi>Eſau Jacob;</hi> and this you may ſee in 1 John 3.10. <hi>In this the Children of God are manifeſt from the Children of the Devil; whoſoever doth not Righteouſneſs, is not of God, neither he that loves not his Brother.</hi> And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.10. where the Apoſtle ſets forth the Children of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will put my Laws into their Mind, and write them in their Hearts; and I will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to me a People.</hi> Now theſe are God's People, of his Elect Seed, and he is their God, who hath written his Law in their Hearts, &amp;c. and this we witneſs, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord for evermore, for his New Covenant, and Work in us.</p>
            <p>And in the next Verſe, ſaith he, <hi>You ſhall not teach every man his Neighbour, and every man his Brother, ſaying, Know the Lord; for all ſhall know him from the Leaſt unto the Greateſt, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo we know, that the Knowledge of the Lord ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Earth as the Waters cover the Sea: For the Lord ſaith, <hi>Look unto me, and be ſaved, all the Ends of the Earth:</hi> Here all are invited to Salvation. And in another place, ſaith he, <hi>I will give him for a Covenant of Light, the Glory
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104399:21"/>of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>and he ſhall be my Salvation to the Ends of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo now the Church is coming out of the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, the Bride, the Lamb's Wife; and the Bride ſaith, <hi>Come;</hi> and the Spirit ſaith, <hi>Come:</hi> Here is the Call to Chriſt the Saviour, who is the Way to God, and there is no other Way to the Father, but by him; neither is there any Salvation by any other Name under Heaven, but by the Name of Jeſus, in whoſe Name we are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and there is no other Foundation to be laid, but what is laid, even Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Top and Corner-Stone, the Foundation of the Prophets, Apoſtles, and us, as is ſaid in <hi>John;</hi> and we are thoſe who have obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Commands of Chriſt, who enlightens every Man that cometh into the World, that all through it might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; who ſaid, <hi>Believe in the Light,</hi> this is his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, <hi>that they may become Children of the Light,</hi> John 12.36. So we know, That as many as receives him (to wit, Chriſt, the Light that enlighteneth every one that cometh into the World) to them gives he Power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Sons of God, <hi>John</hi> 1.12.</p>
            <p>And this we Witneſs, and can ſay, Behold what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Love is this, that we ſhould be called the Sons of God, and Heirs of Chriſt, who makes us ſit together in the Heavenly Places in Chriſt Jeſus, who formerly were dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. <hi>And we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Unction from the Holy One, through which we come to know all things: The Anointing which we have received of him, abides in us; and we need not any ones Teaching us, but as the ſame Anointing does teach us all thengs; and is true, and is no Lye; and even as it hath taught you, ye ſhall abide in him,</hi> 1 John 2.27. It taught the Saints in the Apoſtles
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104399:21"/>dayes, and us in ours; therefore we muſt abide in him, as they did, to wit, in Jeſus. And the Light of Chriſt which ſhines in our Hearts, which God hath commanded to ſhine out of Darkneſs, doth give us the Light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Chriſt Jeſus; And <hi>this is the Heavenly Treaſure we have in our Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Veſſels, that the Excellency of the Power may be of God, and not of us,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6, 7. <hi>So as we walk in the Light, as he is in the Light, we have Fellowſhip one with another, and the Blood of Chriſt</hi> the Son of God (which ſprinkles our Hearts and Conſciences) <hi>cleanſeth us from all Sin,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p>And whereas many Lyes and Scandals you have caſt upon us (to wit) our Denying of God, Chriſt, and the Scriptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They are all Falſe; For <hi>Chriſt</hi> we know, own, and believe his Incarnation, Paſſion, Death, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, Aſcenſion, and Glorification. And the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures</hi> we own to be the Scriptures of Truth; And Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſignifie Writings, and we own the Scriptures to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Words of God which we learn of God, and given forth by the Holy Men of God, and are profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction and Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17.</p>
            <p>And whereas we have been accuſed for <hi>Denying Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin,</hi> and <hi>Owning Perfection here in this Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which we anſwer, That there is an Original of Sin we deny not, but your Doctrine of Original Sin we do deny, as you ſtate it; For doth not Original ſignifie the Beginning, and the beginning of Sin, was it not the <hi>Devil?</hi> For we do affirm, it was neither God, nor Chriſt. And did not Chriſt come to deſtroy the <hi>Devil,</hi> and his Works, and ſo deſtroy the Original. So we muſt tell
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104399:22"/>you, we hold <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and not the <hi>Devil,</hi> who was, and is the Original of Sin and Imperfection; I ſay again, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was before the <hi>Devil</hi> was, who was glorified with the Father before the World began, who bruiſes the Serpents Head, and the Heads of all Deceivers, Lyars, and Slanderers, and Falſe Prophets, and Anti-Chriſts: And in him we are (to wit) Chriſt Jeſus, who is our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Mediator, and Redeemer.</p>
            <p>And as for your Accuſing us for holding <hi>Perfection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. What muſt we not hold <hi>God,</hi> who is <hi>Perfect?</hi> and muſt we not hold <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is <hi>Perfect;</hi> and his Work and Worſhip, which is Perfect; and his Religion which is Perfect, that comes from himſelf; and the Gifts of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> and Grace, and Faith which are <hi>Perfect?</hi> Are not all his Gifts Perfect? and muſt we not receive them in this Life? yea, muſt not our Bodies be the Temple of <hi>God,</hi> and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of his <hi>Holy Ghoſt?</hi> And then muſt we not hold them who are Perfect, and own Perfection? And is not the Command of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to us to be Perfect as our Heavenly Father is Perfect? And was it ever the <hi>work</hi> of the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to preach up Imperfection for Term of Life; but always both the <hi>Prophets, Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> preſſed, and preſſeth us <hi>to Perfection?</hi> and what, do they preſs us to that which is Impoſſible to be attain'd unto? What, will you ſay, that their Words were of no Value? What will you liken Chriſt and his Apoſtles words unto? For were there any that ever denied the Doctrine of Perfection, ſaving only <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, Independants,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſts;</hi> and you, who have got the Forme of Godlineſs, but deny the Power thereof which brings out of Imperfection to the perfect Head <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who is the way to God? And therefore you
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104399:22"/>do not only deny the perfect Power, but alſo are ſhort of having the Form of Godlineſs. And will not <hi>Chriſt</hi> preſent his Church Perfect? <hi>that is,</hi> without Spot, or Wrinkle unto God the Father, who is the pure Head of it? And how will you preſent your Church to God? What, will you preſent it to God with a Body of Death, and a Body of Sin.</p>
            <p>Do not you deny <hi>Circumciſion</hi> in this, namely, the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of the Spirit, that is made without Hands, by putting off the Body of the Sins of the Fleſh, by the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And do not you deny <hi>Chriſt's Baptiſm,</hi> who came with his Fan in his Hand, to purge his Floor thoroughly, whom We ſee is come, and doth increaſe, and do ſee the decreaſe of <hi>John?</hi> I ſay, <hi>He</hi> is come with his Fan in his Hand, who will thoroughly purge his Floor, and burn up the Chaff with unquenchable Fire, and gather his Wheat into his Garner, a ſafe place; And this We witneſs, and ſo muſt all People before they go to their Graves. For this is the Baptiſm that the <hi>Devil</hi> would fain have People to deny, and his Miniſters and Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and then he fils them with Chaff; For as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith to the Church: <hi>By one Spirit we are all baptiſed into one Body, whether we be Jews or Gentiles, Bond or Free.</hi> He doth not ſay, that by Water we were all baptiſed into one Body; For we ſee many Bodies baptiſed with Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Water, and yet do deſtroy one another.</p>
            <p>Now mark the Words, <hi>We are all baptiſed into one Body,</hi> that is, the Church of the Firſt-born, and <hi>Chriſt is the Head of this Body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. So this is the <hi>One Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> ſpoken of Epheſ. 4.4, 5. <hi>There is one Body and one Spirit, even as you are called into one Hope of your Calling, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104399:23"/>who is above all, and through all, and in you all;</hi> Mark that, <hi>Through all, and in you all;</hi> Unto every one of us is given Grace according to the meaſure of the Gift of Chriſt, praiſed be his Name forever: <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> is come by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> yea, that Grace which brings Salvation, which hath appeared unto all men (without Exception) <hi>Teaching us, to deny all Ungodlineſs, and Worldly Luſts, and to live Soberly, and Righteouſly, and Godlily in this preſent Evil World,</hi> Tit. 2.11, 12. And this Grace ſeaſons our Words, and eſtabliſhes our Hearts; So we have a <hi>Teacher</hi> which brings us Salvation, Glory be to God forever and forever. And this <hi>Teacher</hi> is with us where-ever we are, <hi>to wit,</hi> the Grace of God by which we are ſaved, and not of our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And we can ſay, this Grace is Sufficient which brings Salvation, though you look not upon it to be Sufficient, who keep People alwayes under your Teachings, that they may be alwayes Learning of you, and alwayes pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of you, and yet never come to the Knowledge of the Truth in themſelves, nor their Talent in themſelves to improve. For have you not been like the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who ſtopt their Ears, and cloſed their Eyes; and like <hi>Saul,</hi> who kickt againſt that that pricks him, and then kickt againſt others, and perſecuted others? And were they not them who ſhut up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, who would not enter themſelves, nor ſuffer others to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? See that <hi>Bleſſed Doctrine</hi> of Chriſt in <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. who ſaid to them, <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven</hi> (when they deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded when it ſhould come, Chriſt's Anſwer to them was) <hi>comes not with Obſervation, Lo Here, Lo there; But</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven is within you.</hi> And we have found his bleſſed Words to be true; Bleſſed be his Name forever, who hath ſtood at our Door, and knocks, as
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:104399:23"/>He doth at yours; Yea, I ſay, at the Door of our Minds, and at the Door of our Hearts and Souls, and we have let Him in, who now Sups with us, and we with Him, the Heavenly Supper with the Heavenly Man, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven, our Bleſſed Lord, Jeſus Chriſt, and our <hi>Alone</hi> Saviour; O! Glory be to <hi>Him</hi> forever and for evermore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>And you ſay, <hi>There is no Overcoming of Sin and Death on this ſide the Grave, but muſt have alwayes a Warfare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. But did not <hi>Paul</hi> ſay that <hi>He had fought, &amp;c.</hi> then ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>he was not then fighting, he was not then warring,</hi> though 'tis true, Time was that He had been in the War, and led Captive to do thoſe things he would not have done; But if there be no Overcoming on this ſide the Grave, then there is no Eating of the hidden <hi>Manna</hi> on this ſide the Grave, nor no Getting of the <hi>White Stone</hi> on this ſide the Grave, nor of that <hi>New Name</hi> written in the Stone, which no man knoweth ſaving <hi>He</hi> that receiveth it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17. The Reaſon there rendred, becauſe it is <hi>a Gift only to Him that Overcometh,</hi> that is, <hi>on this ſide the Grave.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12, 13. <hi>Him that Overcometh will I make a Pillar in the Temple of my God, and He ſhall go no more out; and I will write upon Him the Name of my God, and the Name of the City of my God, New</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>which cometh down out of Heaven from my God.</hi> So that, mark, this Promiſe will not be made good, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we Overcome on this ſide the Grave; But it may be, you have not the Ears to <hi>Hear what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi> And in the 21. <hi>Verſ. To Him that Overcometh will I grant to Sit with me in my Throne, even as I alſo overcame and am Set down with my Father in his Throne; He that hath an Ear let Him hear what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi> But I fear, you have none of theſe Ears open that the Spirit
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104399:24"/>ſpeaks to here, namely, The Church of the Living God, whereof Chriſt is the Head.</p>
            <p>Again, Rev. 3, 5. <hi>He that Overcometh, the ſame ſhall be Clothed in White Rayment; and I will not blot out his Name out of the Book of Life; But I will confeſs his Name before my Father, and before his Angels: He that hath an Ear, let him hear, &amp;c.</hi> But (as I ſaid before) I queſtion your Ears of hearing what the Spirit ſaith, that there muſt firſt be an Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming: Now this was the Spirit's ſpeaking to the Church that did Overcome.</p>
            <p>But it may be you will ſay, <hi>That the Spirit doth not ſpeak to you in your Church;</hi> and therefore you may queſtion your Church, and your ſelves too.</p>
            <p>And Rev. 2.26. <hi>He that Overcometh and keepeth my Works unto the End, to him will I give Power; and I will give him the Morning Star: He that hath an Ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi> Now we can, and do witneſs that Spiritual Ear, to hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches, Glory to God forever; and we do heartily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that you had the ſame.</p>
            <p>And as for the LIGHT, which you call Natural and Created, and a Made Light, that really and truly is the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, the Heavenly and Spiritual Man; and it is a Heavenly Light and a Spiritual Light, wherewithal He Enlightens every one that comes into the World, which he commands us to believe in, through which we become Children of Light, as was ſaid before: For, in Him was Life (to wit, Chriſt) by whom the World was made, and this Life, that is, in Chriſt, is the <hi>Light</hi> of Men. And ſo, as men are turned to the <hi>Light,</hi> and believe in the <hi>Light,</hi> they are ingrafted into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is the Root or Stock, and they the Branches: So that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:104399:24"/>this <hi>Light</hi> is neither Natural, nor Created, nor Made; for it is the Heavenly Light, which is the Life in Chriſt; by which, we coming into Chriſt the Light, we receive Life. And as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Light,</hi> which was a more Sure Word of Propheſie, whereunto you do well that you take heed, as unto a Light that ſhines in a dark Place, until the Day dawn, and the Day-Star ariſe in your Hearts; ſignifying that this <hi>Light</hi> was ſufficient to bring them unto the Day-dawning, and unto the Day-Star ariſing in their Hearts; yea, this <hi>Light,</hi> that ſhines in a dark Place: And what dark Place was this? and where was it? was it not in their Hearts, which they did well to take heed unto? ſignifying thereby, that they do not well that do not take heed unto it: and ſo, they do well that do take heed unto it; in the Light they ſee more Light, and it ſhines more and more to the perfect Day.</p>
            <p>So this Light that comes from Chriſt, Chriſtians wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it, they receive Chriſt the Bright Morning-Star, which Thouſands do witneſs, and have received Him, Glory to God for evermore; and with their Hearts they do believe, and with their Mouthes Confeſſion is made unto Salvation; and that their Salvation is their Wall and Bulwork againſt all Perſecutors: And ſo, we follow Him, (to wit) <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the Captain of our Salvation, and the Lamb of God that taketh away the Sins of the World; againſt whom the Dragon, Beaſt and Whore, and their Followers are Fighting; but the Lamb will have the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; For He is King of Kings and Lord of Lords, who is the Firſt and Laſt, the Alpha and the Omega, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and the Ending. <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:104399:25"/>
            <head>A Copy of the Prieſts <hi>Petition.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To the Honourable Preſident and Council of his Majeſty's Iſland of <hi>Barbadoes;</hi> the Humble Petition and Addreſs of the Clergy of the ſaid Iſland,</head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THat whereas many of us, in the Publick Diſcharge of our Miniſterial Function, upon the Lord's Day, in the Time of Divine Prayer and Sermon, have been Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and Irreverently Interrupted; and Holy Mother, the Church of</hi> England, <hi>Scandalouſly Vilified, as if ſhe were both in Doctrine and in Diſcipline Falſe, and Erroneous, and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian; the Honeſt and Learned Clergy thereof (even in the Face of their own Congregations) not only taxed as Seducers, Hirelings, Teachers of Lyes, and ſuch like, but Uncharitably Purſued and Anathematized with Words, and Execrations, and Bitter Invectives, by a Baſe Sort of Phanatick People, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly termed</hi> Quakers; <hi>Men, whoſe Practices and Opinions ſeem not leſs repugnant to Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Government, which tends to the Diſparagement of us, and Proſtration of our Order to Contempt; but alſo, and chiefly (which is the ſaddeſt Evil of all) to the Poyſoning, if not the utter Ruin of many Well-meaning Souls in our Flock, who being infatuated and inveighed with their Pernicious Tenents, do deſert the Publick and Conſecrated
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:104399:25"/>Places of God's Worſhip, to with-draw into Private and Unlawful Conventicles, which we are credibly informed they do repair to Duty Four Times in the Week, contrary both to Common and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Laws, and to Acts of Parliament in the Raign of</hi> Edward <hi>the ſixth, Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>and King</hi> James, <hi>and King</hi> Charles <hi>the firſt, and of our now Gratious Soveraign</hi> Charles <hi>the ſecond, in ſuch Caſes Wholſomely Provided.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it therefore pleaſe your Honour, either to Revive and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Statute againſt them; or that ſome other Speedy Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, againſt thoſe Growing Diſtempers, may be conſidered of, whereby our People may be leſs expoſed to the Danger of the Wicked Inſinuations; and our ſelves, by your Pious Care, ſuccoured from ſuch Rude Affronts and Scurrillities; for the future may be Encon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with more Alacrity to proceed in the Faithful Diſcharge of that High Calling, wherein God hath placed us, and we ſhall continue your Daily Chaplins and Orators,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>William Leſsley,</item>
                  <item>John Bernad,</item>
                  <item>William Johnſon,</item>
                  <item>John Hopwood,</item>
                  <item>Mathew Grey,</item>
                  <item>John Page.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Prieſts of this Iſland, about the beginning of the 10th Moneth, 71. did Petition the Aſſembly to make Laws againſt the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and to ſuppreſs them; amongſt which <hi>Will. Leſsley,</hi> and <hi>Will. Johnſon</hi> and Prieſt <hi>VValker</hi> were very active: But after their Paper was read in the Houſe, its credibly affirmed, they were advis'd to put it into their Pockets, leſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> by ſome means or other might procure the Copy of it; and ſo they did, their Deeds of Darkneſs being aſhamed of the Light, leſt it ſhould Reprove them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:104399:26"/>
            <head>Here follows <hi>George Foſter</hi>'s Teſtimony concerning Prieſt <hi>Leſsey</hi>'s Striking and Kicking of him.</head>
            <p>INaſmuch as <hi>William Leſsley,</hi> Prieſt of the Pariſh called St. <hi>John</hi>'s, doth revive his Rage and Malice againſt the People of God called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and againſt the Precious Truth of God, which they hold forth to all, even <hi>That Chriſt Jeſus is the True Light of the VVorld, and that he hath Enlightened all Mankind with a meaſure of his True Light.</hi> I ſay, Inaſmuch as he revives his Rage, I think it not amiſs to revive my Teſtimony, which once I bore againſt him in his publick Houſe of Speaking, ſo far as I was permitted to ſpeak, which is, <hi>That he is no True Miniſter of Chriſt Jeſus, the Lord of Life and Glory; for his Fruits make him ſo manifeſt.</hi> Once I went to his Houſe Civilly, to ask for ſome Goods that were due to me, <hi>and he did fall upon me with ſeveral hard Blows, and with Violence Thrust me out of his Porch, and gave me one bad Kick in the Small of my Back, as I went, or was down the ſteps of the Porch.</hi> Now let all Sober People judge, and to God's Pure Witneſs in all Conſciences I leave it to be judged, Whether Prieſt <hi>Leſsley</hi>'s Dealings with me do not manifeſt him to be one of thoſe whom Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſpeaks of, ſaying, <hi>Many ſhall come in Sheep's Cloathing, but inwardly they are Ravening Wolves; by their Fruits ye ſhall know them.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Foſter.</signed>
               <dateline>This Paper was ſent us about <date>the 26th of the 8th Moneth, 1671</date> ſomewhat before his Death.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:104399:26"/>
            <head>To <hi>VVilliam Leſsley, — VValker, VVilliam Johnſon, VVilliam Frith, — Dyke,</hi> and the reſt of the Prieſts and Miniſters in <hi>Barbadoes.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN much Terderneſs of Love, and Yearning Bowels of Compaſſion, ſome of us called <hi>Quakers</hi> (but indeed <hi>True Chriſtians</hi>) came here to this Iſland (through the Tender Mercy and Good Providence of our Heavenly Father) to viſit our Brethren in Spirit (being thereunto moved by him) as was the Practice of the Servants of the Moſt High, in the Primitive Times, before the Grand Apoſtacy, ſo to do, as you may read in <hi>Acts</hi> 15.36, 37, &amp;c. and verſe 40. <hi>Paul</hi> took <hi>Silas,</hi> being recommended by the Brethren unto the Grace of God.</p>
            <p>Now ſince I have been fully informed, that you (as your Fore-Fathers ever did in Ages paſt) are the Main and Principal (if not the only) Inſtruments in the Hands of Antichriſt, to provoke and incite the Civil and Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Powers here in this Iſland, to draw out their Swords againſt us; to exerciſe, I mean, their Power to diſturb our Peace and Quiet, and to Perſecute us; as we read how <hi>Saul</hi> perſecuted the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 9.1, 2, &amp;c. which great Wickedneſs he acknowledgeth with much <hi>Ingenuity</hi> (after he became <hi>Paul,</hi> a Convert) <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.13. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.9. yea, perſecuted unto Death, and into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Acts</hi> 22.4. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>I was</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:104399:27"/>Perſecutor, and a Blaſphemer, and Injurious; but I obtained Mercy, becauſe I did it Ignorantly in Unbelief:</hi> And even <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, after he (I ſay) became a Convert, and a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Righteouſneſs, was ſorely Perſecuted; but by whom? [Mark] by the <hi>Chief Prieſts and Elders</hi> of the <hi>Jews;</hi> who by one <hi>Tertullus,</hi> their Orator, informed the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor againſt him, ſaying, <hi>We have found this man a</hi> Peſtilent <hi>Fellow</hi> [Mark] <hi>and a Mover of Sedition among all the</hi> Jews <hi>throughout the World, and a Ring-Leader of the Sect of the</hi> Nazarens, <hi>who alſo hath gone about to Prophane the Temple, &amp;c.</hi> Acts 24.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. and in the 14th verſe they call that Way of Worſhip <hi>Hereſie</hi> [mark that] For do not you ſo, if not worſe, of us <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in terming our Miniſtry Hereſie, and Blaſphemy, and what not, as they did his then?</p>
            <p>And you may read how Chriſt himſelf (the Beloved Son of the Father, the Saviour and Redeemer of the World) who did no Sin, who knew no Sin, then whom no man ſpake like) did not eſcape their Perſecution, <hi>viz.</hi> of the <hi>Prieſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, this is plain, that this has ever bin the uſual and conſtant Practice of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> in all Ages, and of the falſe Prophets, falſe Apoſtles, and Clergy, and Miniſters of Antichriſt (who falſly, term themſelves, the True Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt (<hi>Nam eſt haec Tunica Filij tui,</hi> you underſtand me) though certainly Chriſt never ſent them, and ſo conſequently will never own them; to whom he doth and will ſay, namely, to theſe <hi>Prieſts,</hi> that ſay, they Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied in his Name, and in his Name caſt out Devils) <hi>Depart ye Workers of Iniquity, I know ye not.</hi> What ſaith <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 4.28, &amp;c? <hi>But as then, he that was born af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Fleſh perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit</hi> (what follows?) <hi>even ſo it is now.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:104399:27"/>
            <p>Chriſt (I ſay) never ſent ſuch, but Antichriſt (that is, one contrary to, and againſt Chriſt) though they care not to mind or heed it, neither will they believe it: But ſuch are of thoſe that (as Scripture ſaith) Ran be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were ſent; as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.21, 32, &amp;c. <hi>I have not ſent theſe Prophets,</hi> ſaith the Lord; <hi>yet they Ran</hi> [mark that] <hi>I have not ſpoken to them, yet they Propheſied: Behold, I am againſt them that Propheſie Falſe Dreams, and do tell them; and cauſe my People to Err by their Lyes, and by their Lightneſs, yet I ſent them not, and commanded them; therefore they ſhall not profit this People at all, ſaith the Lord.</hi> [Mind that well] For, whom the Lord of Hoſts (who is KING of Kings and LORD of Lords) ſends, commiſſionates, or imployes as Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors upon his Errand, he ſends them <hi>Dove-like,</hi> with an <hi>Olive Branch</hi> of Peace and Love in their Hearts, and with Words of Reconciliation in their Mouthes, out of his Ark; which the Apoſtle terms, <hi>The Miniſtry of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.18. to wit, to Reconcile God and Man, Offended God, and Rebellious Offending Man; to publiſh the Goſpel of Peace, and proclaim Glad-tidings of Good Things, whoſe Feet are Beautiful, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. and Good-will towards poor and undone Man.</p>
            <p>Now conſider, if ſo, how far ſhort do you come (who falſly pretend and profeſs your ſelves to be the Miniſters of Chriſt in theſe our dayes) of the true Apoſtles and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of the Lord Jeſus (the only Ruler of Princes, and Prince of Peace) in that their day? Who notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pretend your ſelves to be Miniſters of Reconciliation, and yet are found and experimented to be Miniſters of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, Diviſions and Perſecutions, even to Naſty Priſons, Bonds and Blood; who, inſtead of putting on the Spiritual Armour, to fight the Lord's Battels, do
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:104399:28"/>Harneſs your ſelves, and prepare War to fight the <hi>Old Dragon</hi>'s, and the <hi>Devil</hi>'s and <hi>Antichriſt</hi>'s Quarrels: Who, inſtead of handling the Sword of the Spirit (which is the Word of God, and Power of God to Salvation) uſe a Sword of Steel; ſo that I may ſay to you, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaid to him (whom he calls an Inſtructer of Fools, and a Teacher of Babes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.20, &amp;c.) <hi>Thou that ſayſt</hi> (or preacheſt) <hi>a man ſhould not Steal, doſt thou Steal? Thou that ſayſt, a man ſhould not commit Adultery, &amp;c.</hi> [Mark well that] So ſay I. Thou that ſayſt, a man ſhould not be Drunk, art thou Drunk? Read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.7, 8. <hi>But they alſo have Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red through Wine, and through Strong Drink are out of the Way: The Prieſt and Prophet have Erred through Strong Drink; they are ſwallowed up of Wine; they are out of the Way through Strong Drink; they Err in Viſion; they Stumble in Judgment; for all Tables are full of Vomit and Filthineſs, ſo that there is no place clean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Thou that ſayſt, a man ſhould not commit Adultery, doſt thou commit Adultery? Read <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.21, 23. <hi>Which Propheſie a Lye unto you in my Name — becauſe they have committed Villany in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and have committed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery with their Neighbours Wives, and have ſpoken Lying words in my Name, &amp;c.</hi> And mind you not, that <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers and Adulterers God will Judge,</hi> Heb. 13.4. And ſuch <hi>ſhall not enter the</hi> Holy City, New Jeruſalem, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
            <p>The Lord I ſay, ſent his Ambaſſadors to proclaim Peace; whereas you ſound forth a Trumpet to Alarum Battels, and to Provoke, Inſtigate and Stir up to Wars, to Fightings and Impriſonings, to Deſtroy, Kill and Murder Nations, and Families, and Perſons in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, even ſuch whoſe Deſires and utmoſt Endeavours
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:104399:28"/>are, to live Peaceably, Harmleſly, and In-offenſively towards God, and towards Men, as they perſecuted <hi>Paul.</hi> And yet, I ſay, ſuch is the <hi>Cain</hi>-like ſpirit of too too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny amongſt you, who ſeek the utter Ruin and Deſtruction, and thirſt after the Blood (which is the Life) of the Poor Deſpiſed People of God: Whereas Chriſt acertains us, (whoſe Steps you ſhould follow, to do Well) <hi>That he came not to Deſtroy Men's Lives, but to ſave them.</hi> But you on the contrary (walking in Antichriſt's Bloody Steps, and ſo contrary to his Noble Precept and Practice) are come it ſeems here to this Iſland not to ſave men's Lives, but to deſtroy them; not to ſeek after their Good, but their Goods; inſomuch that the Inhabitants Eyes begin to be open (which you had ſhut) ſo as that they in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſee your Deceits and Juggles; whereby now you do clearly manifeſt whoſe you are, ſo that he that runs may read; who (as Scripture of Truth ſaith) <hi>Fight with the Fiſt of Wickedneſs:</hi> Whereas an Evangelical <hi>Biſhop</hi> (that is, a True Miniſter of Chriſt) ſhould be <hi>Blameleſs, Sober, and of Good Behavior; not given to Wine, no Striker, nor Greedy of Filthy Lucre, nor Covetous.</hi> Now Mark, Are not you on the contrary guilty of all theſe Things, if not of much more?</p>
            <p>But Friends, let me tell you in Seriouſneſs, That un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you Repent (if it be not too late already, if Time be not paſt, and your Day over; if, I ſay, you be not ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to Deſtruction, as many of God's People witneſs their ſealing up unto Salvation) Repent, I ſay, betimes, ere the Diſmal and Dreadful Decree be gone forth from the Preſence of the Lord againſt you; who are found beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Fellow-Servants (or rather the Lord's Servants, who are not your Fellows) it had been better you never
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:104399:29"/>had been born, as he ſaid of his Betrayer; mind that well; and that a Mill-Stone were hanged about your Neck, &amp;c. you know what follows. For alas! what will become of you, when the Righteous Judge ſhall come to Judgment, who will then (after a <hi>ſtrict Inſpection</hi>) Reward every man according to his Works?</p>
            <p>O! Whither then will you, or can you betake your ſelves, to hide you from the Wrath of the Lamb? when he ſhall ſay, <hi>Bring hither thoſe mine Enemies, that would not have me to Rule over them, and Slay them before me</hi> (this is the Portion of ſuch) You may indeed cry to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and to the Hills, to the Greater, and to the Leſſer, to hide you from Him; but alack! all in Vain: for that will not avail, that will not prove a Sufficient Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; no, it will be (to your great Grief, Horror and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement) found too Short a Covering. If you be (as you pretend your ſelves to be) the true Orthodox, and not Hetrodox (that is, the <hi>True Evangelical Miniſters of Chriſt</hi>) Where are your Evangelical Fruits? Where is your Love, your Righteouſneſs, your Meekneſs, your Patience, your Good-will towards all men, your Good Exhortations in the Way of Peace, with all Long-Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and Forbearance? But inſtead thereof, do you not bring forth the Fruits of the Fleſh? viz. <hi>Envying, Strife, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Contention, Drunkenneſs, Covetouſneſs, Whoredoms, Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Perſecution; rendring Evil for Good, inſtead of rendring Good for Evil; and Curſings for Bleſſings, inſtead of Bleſſings for Curſings.</hi> Of ſuch Chriſt bids us beware of, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.15, 20, &amp;c. <hi>Who come in Sheep's Cloathing, but inwardly are Ravening Wolves; for by their Fruits ye ſhall know them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O! that you would in time think upon the Great Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count (I ſpeak to you as one who wiſhes well, if not
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:104399:29"/>better then your ſelves to your Immortal Souls) that you ſhall, without all controverſie, render to the Lord at the Great and Terrible Day of the Lord. For if the <hi>Death</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> be, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The King of Terrors,</hi> as it is in <hi>Job,</hi> to the Reprobate; O! what will, in that day, that Death be, when Chriſt ſhall ſay unto the Left-Hand Goats, <hi>Depart, ye Curſed, into Everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil, &amp;c.</hi> Why? What's the Matter? Becauſe they viſited not his Impriſon'd Ones; how much more then in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they were the Means and Occaſion of their Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (weigh well his words in <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.) In that, I ſay, he came and found you beating (that is Perſecuting) your Fellow-Servants. O! how then will you be able to appear, and ſhew your Faces before the Lord? who have made it your great Concern, as much as in you lies, to provoke and ſtir up thoſe in Power in this Iſland (as witneſs your ſeveral Petitions to them) to War, Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Trouble the Innocent: Whereas you ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to perſwade people, <hi>To beat their Swords into Plough-Shares, and their Spears into Pruning-Hooks; ſo that Nation might not lift up Sword againſt Nation, neither learn War any more,</hi> Iſa. 2.4. A Mercy which the Lord long ſince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſhould come to paſs, and is now beginning to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled; but endeavoured to be obſtructed by the Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of ſuch as you, but all in Vain: But take heed of limitting the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of with-ſtanding his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, leſt you be found Fighters againſt God; and if ſo, expect that juſtly, with that Apoſtate <hi>Julian,</hi> that may make you cry out with him, in the Anguiſh of your ſpirits, <hi>Viciſti me Galilee:</hi> For know this, That no man ever ſtood it out againſt the Lord, and Proſpered; man has ſtood it out againſt another, and Nation againſt a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:104399:30"/>Nation, and Kingdom againſt a Kingdom, and have Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered; but none ever ſtood it out againſt God, and Proſper'd.</p>
            <p>O! Where is your Love (your Charity, ſo rendred) <hi>that ſuffers long, and is Kind, that Envyeth not, that vaunteth not it ſelf, that is not Puffed up, that behaveth it ſelf not Unſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingly, ſeeketh not her own, is not eaſily Provoked, thinketh no Evil, Rejoyceth not in Iniquity; but Rejoyceth in the Truth, Beareth all things, Believes all things, Hopeth all things, Endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all things:</hi> Of which I may ſay, with your allowed Poet <hi>Terras Aſtrae reliquit,</hi> as <hi>Juſtice,</hi> ſo <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> are departed from you: For where are your <hi>Bowels of Compaſſion?</hi> Have you not rather ſtir'd up others to Fight, and ſet at Variance, &amp;c. that inſtead of a Concord, have ſet at Diſcord? O! what Rents and Diviſions, what Animoſities and Enmities, you, and your Fellows have made over all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> ſo called? Have you not been only Partners, but the chief Fomenters, Complotters, and Broachers of all the Miſchief done? Therefore your Coat, above all other Coats, are like to give an Heavy Account; namely, You of the <hi>Black Robe</hi> here in this Iſland, like the <hi>Chimrims</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Eorum qui nigras induunt veſtes,</hi> as it is rendred in the Margent by <hi>Arius Montanus,</hi> in <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.4. and as <hi>Junius</hi> has it <hi>(Nomen atratorum)</hi> who have ſet all the World at odds, and on Fire; whereas you ſhould have perſwaded them to love one another, and to bear one with another: you have been, I ſay, the Sad Inſtrumens, to learn them Strife and Contention, to teach their Hands to War, and their Fingers to Fight againſt the Lamb and his Followers, who are clothed in White Linnen, which is the Righteouſneſs of the Saints, and of Chriſt; ſo that one Neighbour by your means hath hated another, and ſought the Deſtruction one of another, and Perſecuted and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:104399:30"/>one another, for your Luſts ſake, your Covetouſneſs ſake, your Prides ſake, your Envy your Malice ſake, your Fables ſake, your Corrupt Doctrines and Divinations ſake, which are the Fancies and Product of your airy Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Accurſt Birth of your own fiery Brain, that have been hatcht there, and conceived in the Chamber of your Imagenary, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8.12. theſe being part of the <hi>Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> that men have ſought out, as the Wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.29. and as he who was greater then <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Teaching for Doctrines the Traditions of Men, and ſo make void the Law of God;</hi> to whom you are like in all things, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Picture of your own Father in <hi>John</hi> 8.44. O! where will you abide when the Books ſhall be opened, and all theſe things ſhall in order be ſet before you?</p>
            <p>O! that you would be Wiſe, to conſider your Latter-Ends, ere the Evil Day come (if, I ſay, you Repent not of the Evil of your Doings) <hi>when the Lord ſhall hurl you down, and tumble you head-long into the Bottomleſs-Pit of Perdition; &amp; there forever ſeal you up from the Preſence of the Lord, into the Abiſs, Iſay, of Deſtruction and Eternal Miſery, ſuch as will never have an End, (becauſe Time then ſhall be no more) but after Thouſands of Millions and Miriads of Years are as far from the End of their Miſery, as at the firſt Moment of it; from whence, I ſay, there ſhall be no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption:</hi> No, no; as you have been the Cauſe of all the Righteous's <hi>Sufferings, Impriſonments,</hi> and <hi>Perſecutions,</hi> and <hi>Deaths; you ſhall be Impriſoned there, and bound Hand and Foot, and caſt in there forever,</hi> Luke 11.48, 49, 50. as ſaith the Lord in the Parable of the <hi>Unmerciful Servant</hi> (juſt ſuch Servants many of you are) <hi>Who Treated his Fellow-Servant Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clly, and dealt Hardly with him; whereas his Lord had great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on him, in forgiving him all that he owed him: whereupon his Lord was Wrath, and delivered him to the Tormentors, till he ſhould pay all that was due unto him.</hi> And look as certainly as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:104399:31"/>you have (or ſhall) fill'd any of us with Sorrows and Grief, ſo ſhall you drink the <hi>Dregs</hi> of our Cup, as the Apoſtle ſaith to this purpoſe, <hi>it is a Righteous Thing with God, to Recompenſe Tribulation to them that Trouble you,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.4, 5, 6. You ſhall, I ſay, <hi>drink even of the Wine of the Wrath of God, which is poured out without Mixture</hi> (of the leaſt Pitty or Mercy) <hi>into the Cup of his Indignation, and ſhall be Tormented with Fire and Brimſtone in the Preſence of his holy Angels, and in the Preſence of the Lamb; and the Smoak of their Torment aſcends up forever, and forever; and they have no Reſt Day nor Night.</hi> Can you, Friends, Engliſh that, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14, 10. &amp; 16.5, 6, 7. <hi>MENE TEKEL, You are weighed in the Ballance, and are found light;</hi> ſo writes the Finger of God: <hi>and therefore your Kingdom ſhall be taken from you</hi> (look for it) <hi>and all your Ill-gotten Goods and Eſtates, that by your Lyes, and Falſe Propheſyings, and by ſpeaking Smooth Things,</hi> Iſa. 30.10. <hi>and Daubing with Untempored Morter,</hi> Ezek. 22.28. &amp; 13.9, 10. <hi>and by all your ſowing Pillows under people's Elbows, to Keep and Lull them Aſleep, ſhall all be Vomited up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much I thought meet in Love to write unto you, that ſo you may learn to Fear God, Repent, Believe and Live forever with the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> 
                  <date>the 29th of the 1ſt Moneth, called <hi>March,</hi> 1672.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>From Him that was once of you; but now through Mercy is come out from amongſt you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; and bears this Toſtimony againſt you,</hi> John Hull.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Read</hi> Jer. <hi>cap</hi> 6. <hi>from verſ,</hi> 13. <hi>to</hi> 19. <hi>and</hi> Ezek. <hi>cap.</hi> 34. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 13. <hi>throughout.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript_to_prior_letter">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:104399:31"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <head type="sub">Since the writing of this Letter, I had Information of ſome Sad Paſſages of Prieſt <hi>Walker</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that he Preached before the Rulers of the laſt General <hi>Seſſions,</hi> which occaſioned this <hi>Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>OFRIENDS!</hi> But Seriouſly weigh the Thing in the Cool of the Day, between God and your own Hearts; and Conſider Seriouſly, Whether it be not Sad to See Him, and ſuch who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs your ſelves Miniſters, viz. Chriſt's Ambaſſadours, given to the Churches for Education, Conſolation, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and Inſtruction, to Stand and Appear ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly Diametrically Oppoſite and Croſs to the very End of your Pretended Work and Miniſtry; Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning many of whom I fear it may be ſaid, That <hi>knowingly, wilfully</hi> and <hi>deliberately</hi> Oppoſe Piety and Godlineſs, and Crucifie to themſelves the Son of God afreſh; and have Condemned and Killed the Juſt, that Reſiſted not: O! read that Within. That you ſhould, I ſay, Perſecute, and ſtir up others to Perſecution, whoſe Work ſhould be, To Feed and Preſerve out of it; and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:104399:32"/>Wound, inſtead of Healing; and Grieve the Spirit of the Righteous, who ſhould further their Joy and Comfort: So that ſuch declare themſelves, with open Mouth, to be Phyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ians of No Value.</p>
            <p>And ſo it is made clearly manifeſt, That none are a Greater Plague to the Church (ſo called) both in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting and Deluding it, by your Sorceries and Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and alſo, in cauſing the Sacrifice of the Lord to be by Men abhorred, then ſome of you, who would be accounted, <hi>The SALT of the EARTH:</hi> But, alas! it hath loſt its Savour, ſo that, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>It is good for Nothing, but to be caſt out, and troden under Foot by men,</hi> Mat. 5.13. Luke 14.34. Juſt like thoſe <hi>Prieſts, Eli</hi>'s Sons, Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> by their Debaucheries, Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and Whoredoms, ſpoken of in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.12, 17. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. And inſtead of being <hi>Barnabas</hi>'s Sons of Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, are found and experimented to be <hi>Boanerges</hi>'s Sons of Thunder, Alaruming to War, and to Battels, with Confuſed Noiſe, and Garments rold in Blood.</p>
            <p>O Friends! Be Friendly Adviſed, Not to Sadden the Hearts of thoſe whom God would not have made Sad, <hi>Hazael</hi>-like, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8.11, 12, 13. <hi>Is thy Servant a Dog,</hi> ſaith he to the Prophet, <hi>that I ſhould do this Great Thing.</hi> So Prieſt <hi>Walker</hi> and you may happily ſay, Far be it from any of us, that we ſhould do this Great Thing; that we ſhould Seek, Labour and Endeavour, by Preaching, Teaching or Petitioning the Deſtruction of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: But take heed, take heed, that you be not found amongſt the number of thoſe that think in ſo doing (i. e.) in Killing, Impriſoning, Plundering and Perſecuting them, they do God Service: you cannot be Ignorant that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:104399:32"/>ſuch there were, mention'd <hi>John</hi> 16.2. where ſaith the Lord, <hi>They have put you out of their Synagogues</hi> (that is, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated or Unchurched them, and then Impriſoned them, and Spoiling them of their Goods) as many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds have been by ſuch as you: Yea, the Time cometh, and is it not now? that whoſoever ſhall Kill them, thinks he dorh God Service therein. O! Read and Conſider, leſt you be found, I ſay, to be ſuch; ſuch Fools were thoſe by their own Conſeſſion in the Book of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> which is good Scripture, though placed in that part which is called <hi>Appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chripha;</hi> read <hi>Wiſdom</hi> chap. 5. verſ. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then ſhall the Righteous Man ſtand in great Boldneſs before the Face of ſuch as have Afflicted him, and made no Account of his Labours; when they ſee it, they ſhall be Troubled with Terrible Fear, and ſhall be Amazed at the Strangeneſs of his Salvation, ſo far beyond all that they looked for.</hi> [Mark] Is not this made good now in the Diſappointment of the late ſtrenous En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours and Actings againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> only, of all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters in this Iſland, through the Inſtigation and Promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the greateſt <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Fury</hi> of you <hi>Prieſts</hi> (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of <hi>Prieſt Walker, W. Leſsley,</hi> and his Son in Law <hi>Johnſon</hi>) For, as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, Pſal. 25.20. <hi>They ſpeak not Peace, but Diviſe Deceitful Matters againſt them that are Quiet in the Land:</hi> whereas the Lord ſaith plainly, <hi>Diviſe not Evil againſt thy Neighbour, ſeeing he dwelleth ſecurely by thee,</hi> Prov. 3.29, 30, 31. Weigh this well, and conſider Proud <hi>Hamon</hi>'s De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh Stratagem againſt God's People, and how the Lord Fruſtrated and Diſannulled his deſigned Acts (as he hath, and will do yours) and wicked Diviſes in and to their own Ruin, in the Book of <hi>Eſther,</hi> chap. 8. &amp; 9. according to that <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.15. <hi>He made a Pit, and Digged it, and is fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Ditch which he made; his Miſchief ſhall return upon his own Head; and his Violent Dealing ſhall come down upon his own Pate</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:104399:33"/>(Inſidit in foveam quam ſtruxit) then ſollows, <hi>I will Praiſe the Lord according to his Righteouſneſs, &amp;c.</hi> It being a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Thing in God, ſo to Reward them, whoſe Wayes are Equal, though Man's Wayes are Unequal: And <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.27.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>But to return to that in <hi>Wiſdom</hi> again:</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they Repenting, and Groaning in Spirit, ſhall ſay within themſelves, This was he we had ſometimes in Diriſion, and a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb</hi> (or Parable) <hi>of Reproach; We Fools Accounted his Life Madneſs, and his End to be without Honour; How is he numbred among the Children of God? and his Lot is amongſt the Saints: Therefore we Erred from the Way of Truth, &amp; the Light of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes hath not ſhined unto us, and the Son of Righteouſnes aroſe not upon us: We Wearied our ſelves in the Way of Wickedneſs, and Deſtruction, &amp;c.</hi> O! was not this, Friends, your Work? and will not theſe, or the like, be your Words and Wages anſwerable one Day?</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>John Hull.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:104399:33"/>
            <head>FOR THE GOVERNOUR, And His Council &amp; Aſſembly, And all Others in Power, both Civil and Military in this Iſland; from the People called <hi>QVAKERS.</hi> (With an ADDITION)</head>
            <p>WHereas many Scandalous Lyes and Slanders have been caſt upon us, to the rendring us the more Odious (viz.) <hi>That we do deny God, and Chriſt Jeſus, and the Scriptures of Truth, &amp;c.</hi> This is to inform you, That all our Books and Declarations (that for theſe many years have been publiſhed to the World) do clearly teſtifie to the contrary; but yet, for your ſakes this is now given forth.</p>
            <p>That <hi>God</hi> (who is the Only Wiſe, Omnipotent, and Everlaſting God) we do Own and Believe in, who is the Creator of all things both in Heaven and in Earth, and the Preſerver of all that he hath made; who is God over all, bleſſed forever; to whom be all Honour, and Glory,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:104399:34"/>and Dominion, and Praiſe, and Thankſgiving, both now and for evermore.</p>
            <p>And that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is his Beloved and Only Begotten Son, in whom he is Well-pleaſed; who was Conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, and Born of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> in whom we have Redemption, through his Blood, even the Forgiveneſs of Sins; who is the expreſs Image of the Inviſible God, the Firſt-born of every Creature; by whom were all things created that are in Heaven, and that are in the Earth; Viſible, and Inviſible; whether they be Thrones, or Dominions, or Principalities, or Powers.</p>
            <p>And we do own and believe, that he was made to be as Sin, or an Offence and Curſe for us, who knew no Sin; and was Crucified for us in the Fleſh, without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and that he was Buried, and Roſe again the Third Day, by his own Power, for our Juſtification; and we do believe, that he Aſcended up into Heaven, and now ſitteth at the Right-Hand of God.</p>
            <p>And that this <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and our Foundation; ſo that there is no other Foundation to be laid, but what is laid, even <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> and that he taſted Death for every man, and ſhed his Blood for all men: that he is the Propitiation for our Sins, and not for our Sins only, but for the Sins of the whole World: For ſaith <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> of him, <hi>Behold, the Lamb of God that taketh away the Sins of the World,</hi> John 1.29.</p>
            <p>And we do believe, That he is our Alone Redeemer and Saviour, even the Captain of our Salvation; who ſaves us from Sin, as well as from Hell, and from the Wrath to come, and deſtroyes the Devil and his Works; who is
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:104399:34"/>the Seed of the Woman, that bruiſes the Serpent's Head, to wit, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> who is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he is (as Scriptures of Truth ſay) our Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Juſtification and Redemption; neither is there Salvation in any other; For there is none other Name under Heaven, given among men, whereby we muſt be ſaved: it is he alone who is the Shepherd and Biſhop of our Souls; he it is that is our Prophet, whom <hi>Moſes</hi> long ſince teſtified of in <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22, 23. <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord our God raiſe up unto you, of your Brethren, like unto me, him ſhall you hear in all things, whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto you: and it ſhall come to paſs, that every one that will not hear that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſhall be Deſtroyed from among the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He it is that is now come, and hath given us an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that we may know him that is true; and a Rule in our Hearts, even his Law of Love and of Life in our Inward Parts, which makes us free from the Law of Sin and Death,</p>
            <p>And we have no Life, but by him; For he is the Quickening Spirit, the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven; by whoſe Blood we are cleanſed, and our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſprinkled from Dead Works, that we might ſerve the Living God; by whoſe Blood we are purchaſed. And ſo he is our Mediator, that makes Peace and Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation between God offended, and Us offending; being our Surety of the New Teſtament, and the Oath of God, the New Covenant of Light, Life, Grace and Peace; the Author and Finiſher of our Faith.</p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Heavenly Man, <hi>Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi> God with us, we all own and believe in; whom the High Prieſts raged againſt, and ſaid, <hi>He had ſpoken Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy;</hi> and the Chief Prieſts, and Elders of the <hi>Jews,</hi> took Counſel together, and put him to Death; the ſame
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:104399:35"/>whom <hi>Judas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> betray'd for Thirsy Pieces of Silver, which he had from the Prieſts; who gave a Large Sum of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the Souldiers, to broach a Horrible Lye, namely, that they ſhould ſay, <hi>That his Diſciples ſtole him away by Night, whilſt they Slept.</hi> And after he was riſen from the Dead, you may ſee in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> how that the chief Prieſts and Elders Perſecuted the Diſciples of this Jeſus, for prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Reſurrection:</hi> this (we ſay) is that <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> whom we own to be our Life and Salvation.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now concerning the Holy Scriptures.</head>
               <p>We do believe, That they were given forth by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit of God, through Holy Men of God, who ſpoke (as Scriptures of Truth ſay) <hi>As they were Moved by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1. and that they are to be Read, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and Fulfilled; and he that fulfils them is Chriſt. And are profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs; that the Man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all Good Works, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. and are able (as Divinely Inſpir'd) to make us Wiſe to Salvation, through Faith in Chriſt Jeſus. And we do believe, That the Scriptures are the Word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God; for its ſaid in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.1. <hi>God ſpake all theſe Words, ſaying, &amp;c.</hi> meaning the <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth upon Mount <hi>Sinai:</hi> and in <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. ſaith <hi>John, I te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie unto every man, that heareth the WORDS of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of this Book; if any man addeth unto Theſe — and if any man ſhall take away from the WORDS</hi> (not Word) <hi>of the Book:</hi> So in Luke 1.20. <hi>Becauſe thou believeſt not my WORDS:</hi> and <hi>John</hi> 5.47. &amp; 15.7. &amp; 14.23. &amp; 12.47. So that we call the <hi>Scriptures</hi> as Chriſt and the Apoſtles call'd them, and as the Holy Men of God call'd them, namely, <hi>The</hi> WORDS <hi>of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:104399:35"/>
               <p>Another Slander and Lye they have caſt upon us, is; namely, <hi>That we ſhould teach the</hi> Negars <hi>to Rebel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Thing we do utterly <hi>abhor</hi> and <hi>deteſt</hi> in and from our Hearts, the Lord knows it, who is the Searcher of all hearts, and knows all things; and ſo can witneſs and teſtifie for us, that this is a moſt Egregious and Abominable Untruth.</p>
               <p>For, that which we have ſpoken and declared to them is, to exhort and admoniſh them, <hi>To be Sober, and to Fear God, and to love their Maſters and Miſtreſſes, and to be Faithful and Diligent in their Maſters Service and Buſineſs; and that then their Maſters and Overſeers will Love them, and deal Kindly and Gently with them: And that they ſhould not beat their Wives, nor the Wives their Husbands; nor multiply Wives, nor put away their Wives, nor the Wives their Husbands, as they uſe frequently to do: and that they do not Steal, nor be Drunk, nor commit Adultery, nor Fornication, nor Curſe, nor Swear, nor Lye, nor give Bad Words to one another, or unto any one elſe.</hi> For there is ſomething in them, that tells them, <hi>That they ſhould not Practice thoſe Evils</hi> (or any other) before mention'd: Which if notwithſtanding they ſhould do them, that there are but two Ways; the one, that leads to Heaven, where the Righteous go; &amp; the other, that leads to Hell, where the Wicked and Debancht, Whoremongers and Adulteres, Murderers, Lyars &amp; Thieves go: To the one the Lord of Heaven and Earth will ſay, <hi>Come ye Bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you, from the Foundation of the World;</hi> but to the other he will ſay, <hi>Depart ye Curſed into Everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> The Wicked, into <hi>Everlaſting Puniſhment;</hi> but the Righteous, into <hi>Life Eternal,</hi> Mat. 25.</p>
               <p>Now conſider, Friends, that its no Tranſgreſſion, for a Maſter of a Family to inſtruct his Family himſelf, or elſe, ſome others in his behalf; but rather, that it is a very great Duty lying incumbent upon them: As <hi>Abraham</hi> did, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:104399:36"/>
                  <hi>Joſhua</hi> did; as to the firſt, the Lord ſaid, <hi>I know that</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>will command his Children, and his Houſhold after him; and they ſhall keep the Way of the Lord, to do Juſtice &amp; Judgment, that the Lord may bring upon</hi> Abraham <hi>that which he hath ſpoken of him:</hi> And as for <hi>Joſhua,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.15. <hi>And if it ſeems Evil unto you to ſerve the Lord, chooſe you this Day whom you will ſerve, whether the Godds which your Fathers ſerved, that were on the other ſide of the Flood; or the Godds of the</hi> Amorites, <hi>in whoſe Land ye dwell: But as for me, and my Houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</hi> And further conſider this, That it is a Duty lying upon us, to Pray and to Teach, Inſtruct and Admoniſh thoſe in and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to our Families; it being the Command of the Lord, the Diſobedience to which will incur the Lord's Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; as you may ſee in <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.25. where its written, <hi>Pour out thy Fury upon the</hi> Heathen, <hi>that know thee not; and upon the Families, that call not upon thy Name.</hi> Now <hi>Negars</hi> &amp; <hi>Tauny Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> make up a very great part of <hi>Families</hi> here in this Iſland, for whom an Account will be required at the Great Day of Judgment, when every one ſhall be Rewarded according to his Deeds done in the Body, whether they be Good, or whether they be Evil: In that Day, I ſay, of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, both of the Good and of the Bad, of the Juſt and of the Unjuſt; when the Lord ſhall be revealed from Heaven with his Mighty Angels, in Flaming Fire, taking Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puniſhed with Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Deſtruction from the Preſence of the Lord, and from the Glory of his Power, when he ſhall come to be Glorified in his Saints, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="addition">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:104399:36"/>
               <head>Here follows the <hi>Addition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHereas divers Reproachful Speeches, by ſome of the Prieſts and People of the Iſland of <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does,</hi> were caſt upon <hi>George Fox,</hi> ſince his arrival here; its ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that the <hi>Devil</hi> was the Author of them, to prevent and pervert the Minds of People from the Living Truth of God, and the Right Way to God, to wit, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> of whom the ſaid <hi>G.F.</hi> inform'd the People, that ſo they might all come to inherit Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo inherit the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, viz. Chriſt, their Teacher, their Way, their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet (of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> propheſied long ſince, <hi>That him they ſhould Hear</hi>) their Biſhop, to Over-ſee them; and their Shepherd, to Feed them; and their Miniſter, that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtereth Grace, and Life and Truth unto them; who is their Rock, and Foundation of the Prophets, and Apoſtles, and of us, who in Scorn they call <hi>Quakers;</hi> yea, of that Chriſt, who bruiſed the Serpent's Head, and deſtroyes the Devil and his Works.</p>
               <p>So he is the Way to God, to the pure God, who is the Pure Foundation of many Generations, &amp; is the Life of all Mankind, that have Life; for as they all dyed in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo the Life they have is in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> to wit, Chriſt Jeſus, by whom the World was made; who was Glorified with the Father before the World began.</p>
               <p>Now, I ſay, every one muſt receive him, in whom they have Life Eternal, who is the Son of God; and ſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him, they receive the Faith of the Son of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Blood, that ſprinkles their Hearts and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from dead Works, that ſo they might ſerve God in the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:104399:37"/>new Life in Chriſt Jeſus. I ſay, that Chriſt Jeſus, that was Crucified without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and was Dead and Buried, whom <hi>Judas</hi> betray'd to the Chief Prieſts for <hi>thirty pieces of Silver,</hi> who afterwards aroſe out of the Grave, even the <hi>third day;</hi> though the Magiſtrates and Prieſts ſet a Watch, a Guard of Souldiers upon his Sepulchre; and the chief Prieſts gave the Souldiers large Money to ſay, <hi>That his Diſciples ſtole Him away by Night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I ſay, <hi>is our Life,</hi> who Dy'd for our Sins, and is Riſen for our Juſtification; who remains in the Heavens at the Right hand of God, until the reſtitution of all things: And we ſay, <hi>He is Manifeſted and Revealed in us, and we are in him by his Light, Power and Spirit:</hi> and he hath taught us what to believe in, to wit, <hi>the Light,</hi> as you may ſee in <hi>John,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>He is the Light;</hi> and commands us, <hi>to believe in the Light, that we may be the Children of Light:</hi> And ſo, we are Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in the Light (to wit, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi>) and have the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> within our ſelves: And after we believ'd, we were ſeal'd by the Spirit of Promiſe; and we can ſet to our Seal, <hi>That God is True in all his Prophets and Promiſes, concerning his Son; and the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, that preacht Chriſt's Birth and Life, Miracles, Sufferings, his Death and Reſurrection.</hi> So we do confeſs him before men, to be our Shepherd, our Way, and our Foundation, and the Head of his Church; and he is our Bill op, our Miniſter, and our Prieſt; who is made higher then the Heavens, Holy and Harmleſs: and this we are not aſhamed to confeſs before men.</p>
               <p>Now as for the Filthy and Unſavory words, that have been caſt upon me, they are all Falſe. O! that People ſhould bend their Tongues to invent filthy Lyes, and that others ſhould be given up to believe a Lye: So that Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> of Chriſt is fulfilled, <hi>They ſhall ſpeak all manner of Evil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:104399:37"/>you for my ſake.</hi> But yet this we can truly ſay, <hi>The Lord forgive them, if it be his will, if that they have not ſin'd out their day;</hi> and we do earneſtly deſire their Repentance, if there be any place found for Repentance. But truly, it is much if God's Wrath and his Sore Judgments do not fall heavy upon them in this Iſland; a great meaſure whereof they have ſeen and felt already, and that not long ſince, both by the Plague, that ſwept Multitudes away, as with a Beſom; and by a very great Fire, that burnt down moſt part of the Houſes at the <hi>Bridge:</hi> but we deſire in our Hearts, if it be his Will, <hi>That his Wrath may paſs from them:</hi> And yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, nor do not ſee how well they ſhould eſcape, and go Unpuniſhed, ſince people give themſelves up to ſuch <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucht Talk,</hi> and <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>Slanderous Speeches,</hi> which mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts the Wickedneſs of their Hearts: <hi>For, an Evil Man, out of the Evil Treaſure of his Heart, brings forth that which is Evil; out of the abundance of his Heart his Mouth ſpeaks,</hi> Luke 6.45.</p>
               <p>Now therefore, O <hi>Barbadians,</hi> I Warn you to take heed and Repent, <hi>leſt the Judgments and Wrath of the Lord break out like Fire ſuddainly upon you, and as a Thief in the Night, in an Hour when you little Dream of it.</hi> For alas! I do ſee that that makes my Heart even ready to Tremble almoſt, to ſpeak of the Judgments and Plagues that this Corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture brings upon a Land.</p>
               <p>Where, alas! is Vertue to be found among you? where is Sobriety? where is Moderation? as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>let your Moderation be known to all men; the Lord is at hand,</hi> Phil. 4. where is Modeſty? where is Love Unfeigned? where is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Righteouſneſs (the Bleſſed Fruit of the Spirit of Life and Holineſs) to be found; but rather the Fruits of the Fleſh: O! what a Great Crop may be gather'd of theſe? And ſo that Birth of the Fleſh judgeth of others to be like it ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:104399:38"/>
               <p>Know this, If you Prieſts were the Miniſters of Chriſt, then ſuch things would be Reproved by you, and you and your People would receive us gladly when we come among you in the Name and Fear of the Lord, and Viſit you in Love; and not have raiſed ſuch falſe Report and Wicked Slanders of us, and caſt ſo much Dirt &amp; Filth upon our Faces to mar us: ſo that it is much to be feared, <hi>that you have loſt the Day of your Viſitation;</hi> you having Rejected thoſe whom the Lord hath ſent in Love to Viſit you here: And 'tis no Wonder, conſidering that this has been the Practice of the <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Shepherds</hi> and <hi>Prieſts of Old, to raiſe Lying Slanders upon the Truth;</hi> and ſo do you, as you may ſee all along in the <hi>Scriptures of Truth.</hi> O! what <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>Malice,</hi> what <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> did the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> (who profeſt themſelves, <hi>to be the Children and People of God, and Children of</hi> Abraham <hi>the Faithful</hi>) act againſt the Prophets of the Lord, &amp; againſt Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles? ſee <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.39, 40, &amp;c. But withal, mark their End; what became of them all? its ſaid, <hi>The Name of the Wicked ſhall Rot? but the Name of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall never be blotted out:</hi> and Pſal. 37.35, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And thus you <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and others of your <hi>Gang</hi> (who they are you may gueſs) have broacht &amp; publiſht theſe Lyes and Slanders, whoſe Minds and Tongues ſeem wholy bent to do Miſchief, and to ſpeak Evil of the Righteous: <hi>But a Lying Tongue God abhors,</hi> Pſal. 119.163. <hi>And Tophet is prepar'd of Old for ſuch,</hi> as you may read in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
               <p>Now we may ſay, <hi>What Chriſtianity is amongſt the People here? and what Religion have they been taught?</hi> And truly, this is not <hi>Civil,</hi> nor <hi>Neighbourly done,</hi> of ſuch as have raiſed up theſe <hi>Slanders and Lyes,</hi> whereof <hi>G.F.</hi> was not guilty, nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of them before: ſo that it ſeems, <hi>the Father &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe Lyes are here in this Iſland;</hi> and therefore query, whether you <hi>Prieſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Baptiſts</hi> have not been the <hi>Men-Mid-Wives,</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:104399:38"/>to forward the <hi>birth</hi> of them. O! where is Modeſty, and where is Vertue, that ſhould be in your Minds and Mouthes? where is Truth in your Inward Parts? Yea ſome of theſe <hi>filthy things</hi> have been in the Minds &amp; Mouthes of ſome who have been of ſome Repute amongſt you, yea, and of the Teachers too, which is a very ſtrange thing; had it been only the <hi>rude rabble of people,</hi> it had not been worth the taking notice of; but for ſuch as look upon themſelves, <hi>as Men of Repute amongſt you,</hi> to have ſuch things in your minds and mouthes; it is very ſtrange, had they any regard to their own <hi>Credit</hi> and <hi>Reputation;</hi> though I ſhall name none, but you all know your ſelves who you be: &amp; therefore it is good for you all to Repent of theſe things, and ſeek after Vertue, and after Peace, Truth and Holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee God; and after the Lord Jeſus, who teaches no ſuch Lyes nor Slanders; <hi>but deſtroyes the Lyar, and Author of Lyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another <hi>Slander</hi> they have got up here, <hi>That</hi> G.F. <hi>ſhould Hang Ribbons upon peoples Arms, by which means they were Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witcht;</hi> Which was firſt forg'd by an <hi>Independent Prieſt,</hi> one of <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi>'s News-Mongers, who put it into his Weekly-News-Book: and when he was queſtion'd, where he had the Information; firſt, he ſaid, <hi>it was a Woman,</hi> and then afterwards, ſaid, <hi>it was a Man that told him of it;</hi> but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver could we get from him <hi>the Name of that Man or Woman,</hi> or <hi>of the Town and Country where he or ſhe lived to this day.</hi> And this <hi>Lye</hi> and <hi>Slander</hi> went for credit, it being printed in the <hi>Dyurnal;</hi> and the Prieſts likewiſe publiſht it in their Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits; and others would Swear, <hi>that their Brother Independant Prieſt cauſed it to be put into the</hi> News-Books, when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived many of their Hearers to forſake them, <hi>who would not put into their Mouthes any longer;</hi> therefore they raiſed this <hi>Slander,</hi> thinking thereby, <hi>to caſt a Stumbling-block before the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:104399:39"/>people, to ſtop them from coming to embrace the Truth:</hi> but they were deceived in that; for that manifeſted their Folly the more, and their Lyes and Slanders; and confirmed the people the more in the Truth. And theſe <hi>Independants</hi> were the firſt that gave the Nick-name of <hi>Quakers;</hi> as, one <hi>Bennet</hi> at <hi>Darby,</hi> 1650.</p>
               <p>And then likewiſe they rais'd Slanders, <hi>That we deny'd God and Chriſt, and the Scriptures;</hi> which were all Lyes: and then the <hi>Presbyterians, Independants</hi> and <hi>Baptiſts</hi> ſet their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to Scoff and Mock us; calling us <hi>Tremblers,</hi> and <hi>Shakers</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> in that day, &amp; what not, when they had the <hi>day</hi> of it, the Tythes, and Pulpits and the Power in their Hands. But the Lord God, when he had brought the <hi>King</hi> into his Power, then he ſhook't them out of their <hi>Pulpits, their Tythes, and Eſther-Reckonnings, and Midſummer-Dues, &amp;c. and made ſuch Shaking, &amp; Quaking, &amp; Quivering amongſt them, as Rock't and Shook't them out of their Great Benefices, &amp; laid their Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance levil with the Earth, inſomuch as that they durſt hardly Creep into a Houſe to Meet:</hi> &amp; ſo the Lord hath given them Shaking, and Quaking, and Trembling and Quivering enough, who were the firſt Raiſers of that Nick-name, in calling the People of God <hi>Quakers:</hi> So that they have had a Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Day of Trembling ſince that. And therefore let others take heed, and mind the Example of all theſe Lyars and Slanderers that are gone before them</p>
               <p>And becauſe that G. F. and ſome Maſters of Families, had ſome Meetings with the <hi>Negars</hi> belonging to friends, and did admoniſh them and <hi>Chriſtianly</hi> perſwade them, <hi>that they ſhould be content with having but one wife, each man of them; and that the Wives ſhould love their Husbands, and the Husbands their Wives; and fear God, and not abuſe them, either with blows, or in Bitter Words, and that they ſhould not Steal nor commit for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, or Adultry, nor do any wicked thing; but that they ſhould
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:104399:39"/>Serve and Worſhip the Lord God in Spirit and in Truth, and yield ſubjection to their Maſters, and thoſe over them, and do what they did in Singleneſs of Heart &amp;c.</hi> Whereupon ſome of you Prieſts have raiſed, as we underſtand, a Slander upon Friends, viz. <hi>that we have a Deſign to teach the Blacks to rebel:</hi> which is a moſt falſe Lye; whereas indeed, it ſhould have been their work (who take upon them to be Miniſters of Chriſt) <hi>to admoniſh the Blacks and Taunies themſelves, and preach the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt to them themſelves.</hi> But was not there a great Profeſſor, that ſaid to a <hi>Black</hi>'s Child, <hi>Lord bleſs thee;</hi> and after did ſhe not, as re-calling her words, ſay, <hi>Lord forgive me;</hi> as though the <hi>Blacks</hi> had no ſouls to ſave as well as <hi>Whites?</hi> Its credibly reported that once when a <hi>Black</hi> came to a Steeple-Houſe in time of worſhip, That the Sexton came to him with his Whip, and ſaid unto him, <hi>Get thee out thou Dog; what do you here?</hi> are theſe the words of Chriſt? for ſure <hi>the Lord Would have all to be ſaved:</hi> And have you no Goſpel for <hi>Blacks?</hi> is not the Goſpel to be preached to all Nations and peoples? and are not the <hi>Blacks</hi> of ſome Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and people? did not Chriſt dye for the <hi>Blacks</hi> and the <hi>Taunies,</hi> as well as for the <hi>Whites?</hi> and was not his Blood ſhed for all men, and are they not men? And muſt Chriſt be preacht to ſome people and not to ſome others? And as for <hi>deſigns</hi> we deny, diſown and abhor all ſuch things: We deſire that all may live Peaceable under the Governors of their reſpective Families, and under the Government of the Iſland and nations wherein and amongſt whom they are; for we are ſo taught of Chriſt, namely, <hi>to ſeek the good of all men, and peace with all men.</hi> And we would have all men to be ſaved, as well as our ſelves. <hi>And we Covet none of the People's Money, neither Gold nor Silver,</hi> as you Prieſts do; but as <hi>freely we have received,</hi> ſo <hi>freely we give:</hi> For we do not come into a Pariſh, to make the People and their goods
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:104399:40"/>our Free-Hold for term of life, as yours do; and pretend and make the people believe, that <hi>we do watch for their ſouls</hi> as yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prieſts do, <hi>and yet never intend it;</hi> but watch when the <hi>harveſt comes</hi> that you may ſhare in their goods and eſtates that God hath bleſt them with encreaſe: And as you know they do in other places, watch when the Sows pig, that they may have the Tythe Pig, and the Tythe Egs, &amp;c. and watch when the Turkies and Hens hatch, that they may have ſome of the encreaſe of the Chickins, and Gog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, &amp;c. this is that they watch for; And watch when the Corn is ripe, and the cocks of hay are made, this is that they Gape for, <hi>gain from their quarter as of old, for their goods, and not for the good of their ſouls;</hi> which if a man give them not, nor put into their Mouths, <hi>then they prepare war againſt them.</hi> This, I ſuppoſe, is well known here, and theſe are the Souls they watch for; and where they find a bigger Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, thither do they go; for ſuch things it is they watch for; and ſo, as the old Proverb is, <hi>No Penny, no Pater Noſter:</hi> For <hi>what Pater Noſter have any had of you Prieſts, without a Penny</hi> in this Iſland? Have you not thrown away that Command of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Freely you have received, freely give?</hi> And have you not come ſhort of the Example of <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.33. <hi>I have Coveted no man's Silver, or Gold, or Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel</hi> (Yea, your ſelves know, <hi>That theſe Hands have miniſtred to my Neceſſities, and to them that were with me) that ſo he might be an Example to all that followed him.</hi> So that I ſay, Such have not follow'd the Apoſtle in this particular: But is not <hi>Demas</hi> your Example, <hi>who forſook the Truth, and embraced the things of this preſent World?</hi> And the Falſe Prophets and Shepherds, are they not your Example, <hi>who ſeek for their Gain from their Quarter, and Horſleech like, think they can never have enough;</hi> read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. throughout: <hi>And ſeek for the Wool and the Fleece, and to make a Prey of the Sheep;</hi> read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. cap.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:104399:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>And preach for filthy Lucre, for Hire, for the Love of Money, that mind Earthly things, who are Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> theſe are the things that ſuch watch for, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple's Souls; and to get and preſent theſe outward things into their Barns and Houſes, and not to preſent their Souls to God, as the True Miniſters did and do: and if any one would not give them their <hi>Hire,</hi> though they never ſet them a work, they would Perſecute them, and Cry Out for the Magiſtrate's Power to aſſiſt them: So that are not ſuch as theſe next a kin to the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Begging Friars;</hi> for do they not Beg of the Magiſtrate, for their Tythes or Maintenance to be paid them? And was not the firſt riſe of Tythes from the Pope? who raiſed up and inſtituted that Order of <hi>Fryar Mendicants,</hi> ſince Chriſt's and the Apoſtles dayes, who ſaid, <hi>Freely you have received, freely give.</hi> So read <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. &amp; <hi>Tim.</hi> &amp; <hi>Titus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mich.</hi> 3. and ſee whoſe Steps ſuch Miniſters walk in; and <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. throughout; and ſee if you do not walk in the Steps of them, againſt whom Chriſt pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſuch Heavy, Dizmal and Dreadful Woes.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
